<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Abdicated prince, or, The adventures of four years a tragi-comedy, as it was lately acted at the court at Alba Regalis by several persons of great quality.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75944</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A71A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43588</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42474995</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42474995</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151096</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75944)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151096)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2243:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Abdicated prince, or, The adventures of four years a tragi-comedy, as it was lately acted at the court at Alba Regalis by several persons of great quality.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[4], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Carterson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A political satire relating to James II and the Duke of Monmouth.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701 --  Drama.</term>
               <term>Monmouth, James Scott, --  Duke of, 1649-1685 --  Drama.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688 --  Drama.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151096:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Abdicated Prince;</hi> OR, THE ADVENTURES of FOUR YEARS. A Tragi-Comedy, As it was lately Acted at the COURT at <hi>ALBA REGALIS, By ſeveral Perſons of Great Quality.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—Nec Lex eſt juſtior ulla</l>
               <l>Quam necis artifices arte perire ſua.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Carterſon,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:151096:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151096:2"/>
            <list>
               <head>THE Actors Names.</head>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <head>The MEN.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cullydada,</hi> King of <hi>Hungaria Nova.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Philanax,</hi> his true Friend and Counſellor, but out of Favour.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Philodemus,</hi> Duke of <hi>Monumora,</hi> the Darling of the People.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pietro,</hi> a ſly malicious Villain; a Renegado Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and turn'd a Mahometan Prieſt, chief Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of the Kings, and a Mortal Enemy to the <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Count <hi>Dadamore,</hi> a ſpecial Favourite of the Queens, an <hi>Italian</hi> by Birth, and ſent on a Secret Meſſage by the <hi>Mufti</hi> to the <hi>Hungarian Court.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Barbaroſſa,</hi> Chancellor of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> a bloody-minded Villain, and Enemy to the Chriſtians.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Warranto</hi> Two Creatures of the Chancellors, rais'd on purpoſe to ruine the Laws and Liberties of the <hi>Hungarians.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Diſpenſo</hi> Two Creatures of the Chancellors, rais'd on purpoſe to ruine the Laws and Liberties of the <hi>Hungarians.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Remarquo,</hi> an Honeſt <hi>Hungarian;</hi> a deep Obſerver of the Court Intrigues, who by a Witty ſort of Buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foonry
<pb facs="tcp:151096:3"/>picks out and diſcovers all their Plots and Contrivances.</item>
                     <item>Sentinels, Rabble, Meſſengers, Country-People, Officers.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <head>The WOMEN.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hautefelia, Queen</hi> of <hi>Hungary,</hi> a proud imperious bloody minded Woman, ſworn Enemy to the Chriſtians of <hi>Hungary,</hi> in Love with Count <hi>Dadamore.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mazeto,</hi> Marchioneſs of <hi>Bulgaria,</hi> chief Confident of <hi>Hautefelia.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sycophante, Counteſs</hi> of <hi>Shambrogue,</hi> and Favourite of <hi>Hautefelia.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Celia,</hi> Midwife to the <hi>Queen.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Secretta,</hi> Nurſe to the <hi>Queen.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151096:3"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Abdicated Prince;</hi> OR, THE ADVENTURES OF FOUR YEARS</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACT I.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SCENE I.</hi> The Curtain being drawn, the King and Queen are diſcover'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Scenes, riſing as it were from a private Banquet, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing forward on the Stage. The Queen begins.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                     <l>NOW the great Buſineſs of my Life is over;</l>
                     <l>That Clog to all my <hi>Cullidada</hi>'s hopes,</l>
                     <l>That ſtill kept down and aw'd my aſpiring heart,</l>
                     <l>Is now remov'd with ſilence and with ſafety:</l>
                     <l>And now my active Free-born Soul's at liberty.</l>
                     <l>Yes, <hi>Cullidada,</hi> he is gone indeed;</l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:151096:4"/>
                     <l>But you muſt needs confeſs with gratitude</l>
                     <l>My active prompting Tongue did firſt inflame</l>
                     <l>Thy ſhrinking Soul with courage and with reaſon.</l>
                     <l>Time and Intemperance, thou'dſt often ſay,</l>
                     <l>Will ſoon perform (and that without our Crime)</l>
                     <l>The utmoſt of our Wiſhes and Deſires:</l>
                     <l>But ſtill thou would'ſt forget the falling ſnow</l>
                     <l>That then in flakes lay thick upon thy head,</l>
                     <l>Which the faint warmth, alas! of thy chill'd ſpirits</l>
                     <l>Will ne're, I fear, be able yet to thaw;</l>
                     <l>And would'ſt thou not my <hi>Cullidada</hi> grieve?</l>
                     <l>Nay, if (as our moſt holy Prophet tells us)</l>
                     <l>There's ſenſe of pain and pleaſure after death,</l>
                     <l>Would it not make thy Paradiſe a Hell,</l>
                     <l>To ſee thy vaſt ambitious Soul ſhrink back,</l>
                     <l>And skulk and herd with the ignoble crowd</l>
                     <l>Of uncrown'd Heads?</l>
                     <l>I grant indeed that Nature do's encroach,</l>
                     <l>And ſometimes would confine our Appetites;</l>
                     <l>Honour, Religion, Friendſhip too ſometimes</l>
                     <l>(Thoſe bugbears of the crafty Prieſt's creatio</l>
                     <l>Will needs intrude to regulate our Fancies;</l>
                     <l>But theſe, alas, were at the firſt deſign'd</l>
                     <l>To influence the crowd, and to amuſe</l>
                     <l>The giddy Rabble, while the King goes free,</l>
                     <l>And acts according to his inclination.</l>
                     <l>Tell me, did e're the <hi>Mufti</hi> (our High Prieſt,)</l>
                     <l>When any powerful Monarch did demand</l>
                     <l>Even what the moſt licentious would forbear,</l>
                     <l>Provided always it did not detract</l>
                     <l>From his own Glory, Intereſt and Power;</l>
                     <l>Tell me, I ſay, did ever he refuſe,</l>
                     <l>Or with a tardy niggard hand ſend back</l>
                     <l>His Bulls, Indulgences, and Diſpenſations?</l>
                     <l>From this it follows, what the Monarch Wills,</l>
                     <l>Is Law and Equity of courſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151096:4"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>King.</speaker>
                     <l>Well <hi>Hautefelia,</hi> I muſt praiſe thy care</l>
                     <l>To make my Crown ſit eaſie on my head;</l>
                     <l>But I confeſs it ſomething puzzles me,</l>
                     <l>(And yet I want not Heart or Reſolution)</l>
                     <l>To think in what a world of difficulties</l>
                     <l>We ſtand engaged.</l>
                     <l>'Tis true, the glorious luſtre of a Crown,</l>
                     <l>Which by the eaſie temper of my Brother</l>
                     <l>I grew acquainted and familiar with,</l>
                     <l>Did ſo awaken my ambitious thoughts,</l>
                     <l>And rais'd ſuch murmuring conteſts in my breaſt,</l>
                     <l>As made me at the laſt become his Rival:</l>
                     <l>Then as two Friends, who when they have agreed</l>
                     <l>To ſhare the pleaſures of a beauteous Miſtreſs,</l>
                     <l>Do yet with jealous eyes attend and watch,</l>
                     <l>Each fearing and ſuſpecting partial Favours;</l>
                     <l>So I began to blame my unjuſt Fortune</l>
                     <l>That by a trick of Elderſhip had given</l>
                     <l>What my bold Genius told me I deſerv'd,</l>
                     <l>Nay, and deſerv'd alone.</l>
                     <l>Then ſtill as my diſlike grew on, the faults</l>
                     <l>And weakneſs of my Rival, (as I thought)</l>
                     <l>Encreas'd and multiply'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis well, you ſay</l>
                     <l>You ſaw theſe faults, and yet could tamely ſtand</l>
                     <l>And wait the formal ſtroak of tedious time,</l>
                     <l>E're boldly graſp at what you thought your due.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Pietro, Barbaroſſa, <hi>at one door,</hi> Remarquo <hi>at another.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <l>Yet, <hi>Hautefelia,</hi> I in time grew wiſe</l>
                     <l>And nick'd the happy Minute—</l>
                     <l>With thy bold Counſels, and my own Ambition</l>
                     <l>Prompted, I made a quick advance,</l>
                     <l>Did I not <hi>Barbaroſſa?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:151096:5"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Barb.</speaker>
                     <p>Why truly Sir, by the neatneſs of the Contrivance, and quickneſs in the Execution, a body would think your Majeſty was no Learner in the Trade of packing off Elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <p>You know the manner, ſo I'le hold my Tongue.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Remarquo,</speaker>
                     <stage>[aſide.]</stage>
                     <p>Oh had reſtraining Providence ſo held your hand! May it pleaſe your Majeſty to hear your honeſt old Servant ſpeak a word or two?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <p>Speak on.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>I have a ſcurvy Brother, who in a ſmall diſpute about Priority, even in my Mothers Belly, gave me a ſwinging box on the Ear, before I was aware, and by the advantage of that blow ſlipt into the World before me, and enjoys three thouſand a Year in my prejudice; nay, though he has had the Ptyſick, and labour'd under a Conſumption theſe fourteen Years, has neither Chick nor Child, and can't ſpend the Tithe of his Rents, yet he won't give me a farthing to maintain me, and would as ſoon invite a Captain and his Troop to Free-quarters in his Houſe, as me to take ſhare of a Bottle of his Wine, or a Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſs-dinner: Now Sir, here are your Chancellour and Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, two Perſons of Notorious Conſcience and Piety, they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand my Caſe, and I beg your Majeſties favourable deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Here</hi> Barb. <hi>and</hi> Pietro <hi>ſhuffle up in haſt to</hi> Remarq. <hi>and both whiſper him.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Barb.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I know your Caſe very well, and if you would bring it before me, I ſhould bring your Brother to reaſon; three thouſand a Year, ſay you, and ſo inhumane to his only Brother? But I will be your Friend, not that I expect to be much a gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, though I confeſs it will be a troubleſome point: Three thouſand a Year, ſaid he, <stage>[aſide this]</stage> A Man might pick up a handſome Portion for his Daughter out of it, and egad we muſt provide for thoſe of our Houſhold, as they ſay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Pietro</hi> to <hi>Rem.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <stage>[aſide.]</stage>
                     <p>Sir, your Caſe appears hard and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, but I could put you into preſent enjoyment of two thirds of it, if I could be ſure of the other.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:151096:5"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <p>Well Gentlemen, you muſt be kind to our old Servant, I know him honeſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Exit</hi> King, Queen, <hi>with</hi> Barb. Pietro, <hi>manet</hi> Remarquo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Remarq.</speaker>
                     <p>Now have I brought my ſelf into a fine Praemunire, I have given them a hint of three thouſand a Year, and I ſhall have them as troubleſome to me as a hungry Kite to a brood of young Chickens: Oh! how they catch'd at the word, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was well out of my mouth; and o' my Conſcience will quarrel about the Dividend, though I have no more an Eſtate to lay claim to, than they have a ſtock of Conſcience or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty: I ſpoke to fathom his dealing with his Brother, who is more than ſuſpected to have had foul Play ſhown him; and though Men of leaſt Conſcience are commonly moſt quick of apprehenſion, yet for ought I could perceive they ſtumbled at my Parable, which I am glad of: Diſcretion muſt be the Badge of my Office, and Diſſimulation the Dark Lanthorn to guide me.</p>
                     <l>And ſure 'tis an excuſable deceit,</l>
                     <l>Diſſembling to do good does ſanctifie the Cheat.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE II.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Queen <hi>and</hi> Mazato <hi>talking.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou always bring'ſt me ſome good News or other,</l>
                     <l>I fear'd that Cloud that for ſome Years ago</l>
                     <l>Hung on the haughty proud <hi>Hungarian</hi>'s brow</l>
                     <l>Would ended in a Storm, but now I ſee</l>
                     <l>The Sun-ſhine of our better Fortune has</l>
                     <l>Diſpell'd thoſe noiſome Vapours that did threaten us.</l>
                     <l>But tell me, dear <hi>Mazato,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Does not the freſh remembrance of a Prince</l>
                     <l>That ſometime was the darling of their Hearts</l>
                     <l>Looſen their Tongues, and raiſe their poyſon'd Venom?</l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:151096:6"/>
                     <l>How do they take this loſs?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
                     <p>Then to be plain, if he had dy'd ſeven Years ago, half the Women in the Town had run mad for him, but of late years theſe plaguy Politicians have kept ſuch a pother about Sham-Plots, private Leagues, and a deal of ſuch ſtuff, and going home to their Wives have told ſuch lamentable Stories of him as quite turn'd their Hearts againſt him; and your Majeſty knows poor ſilly Women are apt to believe any thing, God help them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>But dear <hi>Mazato,</hi> tell me how they like</l>
                     <l>This taſt of Government from <hi>Cullidada?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Methoughts their ſhouts went up unanimous,</l>
                     <l>Their Joys exceſſive, and their Welcoms hearty,</l>
                     <l>(As if the Memory of all paſt quarrels</l>
                     <l>Had been no more)</l>
                     <l>When we aſcended the Imperial Throne</l>
                     <l>All Innocent, and all Divine they cry'd,</l>
                     <l>As if that ſaying were Prophetical,</l>
                     <l>That Crowns wipe off all ſtains.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, yes,</l>
                     <l>Like Spaniels, while at diſtance they behold</l>
                     <l>The awful frown of their incenſed Maſter,</l>
                     <l>They'll cringe and creep to their acknowledg'd Duty:</l>
                     <l>Yes, yes, th' <hi>Hungarians</hi> are all Obedience.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis well, and much agrees with our deſigns,</l>
                     <l>And yet my boading Soul foretells</l>
                     <l>There's ſomething wanting to compleat my bliſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Here the Queen ſits down in a Chair muſing.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>Now have I a months mind to be gueſſing what this can be: Stay, I ſhall judge by my own wants: Well, <stage>[ſhe muſes and ſhrugs.</stage> the firſt Happineſs a body would wiſh for, is a guilt Coach and ſix, to whisk thorough the City on a State-day, and make the Ladies teeth water in the Balconies; but hang it, ſhe has that already, and ſo have I, ſo that can't be it: Well then, <stage>[ſhe muſes again.</stage> let me ſee, Money I have enough, and fine Cloaths, and ſo has ſhe, though to ſpeak the plain truth, I believe her Majeſties Name,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151096:6"/>as well as mine is upon many an honeſt poor Citizens Tally. Now ſorrow take me if I can hit it, unleſs it be— <stage>[ſhe pauſes a while]</stage> Oh! what a Jade was I to miſs the <stage>[running up to</stage> main point! Give me leave Madam, I have found <stage>(the Queen.</stage> out your Majeſties want; Oh that I ſhould forget my dear <hi>Tommy!</hi> well, he was a ſweet Lad, Madam, ſo good Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and Efack a Man of buſineſs, ay, ay, <hi>Tommy,</hi> Efack I would have <hi>Tommy</hi> of all things in the World; I knew I could give a gueſs at your Majeſties meaning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Why how now <hi>Mazato,</hi> thou doſt ſurely rave.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, but I humbly beg your Majeſties Pardon, I have been your Majeſties faithful Subject and Servant a long time, and I would not tell your Majeſty a Lye for the World; when ever I think of my dear <hi>Tommy,</hi> 'tis a ſort of Hell to want him; to be ty'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> Old Man that ſpends the beſt part of his Life in ſupping of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>dles, and ſweating in Flannel, that has a good Diſh of Meat before him, and has hardly the ſtrength to ſay Grace to it; to go to Bed before Star-light, and lye 'till high Noon, and all the while lye as ſtill as if you had drank Opium; and if the fit took you, and you reſolv'd to be merry, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Comfort you could have, would be to dance to the Muſick of his Noſe: This is intolerable.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! prithee ſtop <hi>Mazato,</hi> thou haſt touch'd me to the quick; ſure nothing but experience could ſo well delineate the Torments of uneaſie Wedlock and yet thou haſt only touch'd my ſmalleſt ſore: Oh! my <hi>Mazato</hi>—</p>
                     <l>Let thy more active Fancy paint</l>
                     <l>What my unapter Tongue can ne're expreſs,</l>
                     <l>Suppoſe the ſorrow of ſome ſleeping Miſer,</l>
                     <l>Who when his airy Fancy in a Dream</l>
                     <l>Has ſhewn him mighty heaps of wiſh'd for Treaſure,</l>
                     <l>With greedy haſt purſues the pleaſing Object,</l>
                     <l>And with a murmuring fearful Joy approaching,</l>
                     <l>Has ſtretch'd his longing Arms thinking to graſp it;</l>
                     <l>When lo his waking faculty returns,</l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151096:7"/>
                     <l>(The Sun that diſſipates his golden miſt)</l>
                     <l>And all his Joys, like ſome enchanted Caſtle vaniſh;</l>
                     <l>Such is, my Dear, thy <hi>Hautefelia</hi>'s Caſe,</l>
                     <l>So tranſitory are the hopes I build on,</l>
                     <l>The pleaſing Viſion which did ſo rejoyce,</l>
                     <l>Which ſhew'd me Mountains of delight and eaſe,</l>
                     <l>Mountains, <hi>Mazato,</hi> that like little Worlds</l>
                     <l>Seem'd ſolid and immoveable,—</l>
                     <l>Is paſt, <hi>Mazato,</hi> 
                        <stage n="*">ſhe muſes a little.</stage> —is it not?—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <p>Now let me be far enough, Madam, but you muſt give me leave to tell you, your Majeſty raves, as you call it: Paſt, ſay you? in the Name of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> what is paſt? I'le fetch it again if it be above ground, I'le warrant you. But by <stage>[aſide</stage> the by, now I think on it, I wiſh my Commendation of honeſt. <hi>Tommy</hi> has not got me a Rival; come, come, let me tell you, Queens are Fleſh and Blood as well as other Women, and as high as her Majeſty looks, I caught her gnawing the Sheets t'other day, and that is a ſhrewd ſign, let me tell you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Queen muſing.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Doſt mock me <hi>Mazato?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Sycophante <hi>and Count</hi> Dada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more <hi>appear at the door.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Syc.</hi> to <hi>Da.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, I'le ask your Lordſhips Pardon, 'till I acquaint her Majeſty with your attendance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                     <p>I wait with Impatience.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Sycophante.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syc.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha! Muſing? Well, I ſhall quickly put her out of her Dumps; this Count <hi>Dadamore</hi> is the Spark ſhe has ſo <stage>[aſide.</stage> often told me of, now he is come with abundance of buſineſs, and I'le warrant it private enough; or to ſpeak it in other words, he has writ her a <hi>Billet Deux,</hi> and for the better ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity has brought it himſelf: Well, I'le e'ne do as I would be done by; bring 'em well together, make my honours, and ſhut the door after me, and when her Majeſty cryes out, I'le come in and ſee fair play. May it pleaſe <stage>[making up to the Queen.</stage>
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:151096:7"/>your Majeſty, Count <hi>Dadamore</hi> waits at the door, and begs the Honour of kiſſing your Majeſties hand.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Conduct him in with ſpeed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Syc.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Now Honour, Virtue, Modeſty defend me;</l>
                     <l>For this is he, <hi>Mazato,</hi> this is he</l>
                     <l>That by ſome ſtrange myſterious art</l>
                     <l>Has taken all my Senſes Captive.</l>
                     <l>Retire in pity, dear <hi>Mazato,</hi> do,</l>
                     <l>And covet not to ſee thy Sex's weakneſs:</l>
                     <l>No, ſtay, and ſee that lovely charming Man,</l>
                     <l>And praiſe the judgment of my well laid choice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Count</hi> Dadamore <hi>and</hi> Sycophante.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                     <l>It were a Crime to think, illuſtrious Queen,</l>
                     <l>The ſmall addition of a trifling Crown</l>
                     <l>Can make a change in <hi>Hautefelia</hi>'s Breaſt,</l>
                     <l>Who ſtood before in Natures Roll of Worthies,</l>
                     <l>The firſt and chief.</l>
                     <l>'Tis in this Faith the happy <hi>Dadamore</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Amongſt the Croud of your admiring Slaves</l>
                     <l>Begs leave to kneel, and pay his adoration.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Syc.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Riſe noble Count, and think th'<hi>Hungarian</hi> Crown Shall ne're make us forget our Friends or you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <stage>[aſide.]</stage>
                     <p>A good ſturdy Fellow Efack, he has ſhoulders ſo like my <hi>Tommy,</hi> I'll warrant him no flincher: See what a Noſe he has, true <hi>Roman</hi> Efack, I'll be hang'd but he brought that Noſe with him, on purpoſe to delude the poor Women here; an arch Wag, he knew what would pleaſe our <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Ladies: No, no, that Noſe never fails.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>aſide</hi> 
                     </stage>
                     <l>Oh! my Prophetick Fears; how coldly ſhe ſpoke.</l>
                     <stage>to the Queen.</stage>
                     <l>I can't ſuppoſe Impoſſiblities,</l>
                     <l>The brave and generous by nature act</l>
                     <l>With decent courteſie to all alike;</l>
                     <l>And common Gratitude obliges all</l>
                     <l>To think with ſeparate kindneſs of their Friends;</l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:151096:8"/>
                     <l>But yet (forgive me if my juſt Deſpair</l>
                     <l>Prompts me too freely to expreſs my grief)</l>
                     <l>Thoſe Favours which your early Bounty gave,</l>
                     <l>And which you often promis'd ſhould continue,</l>
                     <l>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>. (alas! miſtaken Wretch!) believe</l>
                     <l>That ſomething more than barely <hi>not forget</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Might be allow'd to <hi>Dadamore</hi>—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Taxing my Gratitude you ſeem to own</l>
                     <l>Your merit gain'd, thoſe Favours which you boaſt,</l>
                     <l>But I ſhall—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, the weak Policy of Woman! that for <stage>[aſide</stage> a trifling form of Modeſty can thus endure to wrack them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others; as if Men did not ſee through our Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>web Arts of Scorn and Cruelty: Now will I be hang'd, for all her mincing, but her Teeth water to be at him: And for his part, he knows her mind ſo well, I'll warrant him for hanging or drowning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Qu.</hi> to <hi>Maz.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>You may retire, <hi>Mazato,</hi> while he imparts his buſineſs to us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <p>I am all Obedience. Did not I tell you what <hi>[aſide</hi> all theſe hard Words would come to? I knew it by my ſelf, for I ſerve my <hi>Tommy</hi> ſo now and then: We Women of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour don't tread the honeſt beaten paths of Love, but by little tricks, and turnings and windings, we decoy our Gallants in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Snare, and by the like Tricks, when either our Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are pall'd, or their Courages cool'd, we let them looſe, and turn 'em out again, for 'tis not the faſhion to be conſtant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Mazato.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                     <l>Might I preſume to lay aſide the Queen,</l>
                     <l>And with my wonted Liberty approach</l>
                     <l>My generous <hi>Hautefelia;</hi> I would ask,</l>
                     <l>From what neglect of Duty or of Love</l>
                     <l>This Cruelty and Coldneſs can proceed?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>If noble <hi>Dadamore</hi> were ſtill the ſame,</l>
                     <l>As when his <hi>Hautefelia</hi> gave her heart,</l>
                     <l>The Conſcience of his Merit had allay'd</l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:151096:8"/>
                     <l>All Scruples that a jealous Love could raiſe,</l>
                     <l>And fix'd in that belief, could ne're ſuppoſe</l>
                     <l>She'd covet change, who by that change would loſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! ceaſe, alas! that word has puniſh'd more</l>
                     <l>Than your miſtaken Cruelty before;</l>
                     <l>I ſee with Horror, and confeſs my Crime,</l>
                     <l>And own your Goodneſs, like your Bounty, infinite.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, no more, I can believe you love me, nor ſhould I bluſh to own that you are not indifferent to me; time preſſeth me, and I can ſay no more at preſent than this, that ſome important buſineſs will make me exact your Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance very ſpeedily, in the mean time go and be diſcreet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Dadamore.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Queen, ſola.</speaker>
                     <p>Who waits there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mazato, Sycophante.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>What is't a Clock <hi>Sycophante?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syc.</speaker>
                     <p>By my Eyes I ſhould gueſs 'tis almoſt Bed-time, but your Majeſty looks like a Roſe juſt waſh'd in the Morning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dew, ſo blithe, and freſh, and lively, I gueſs the Count has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyc'd your Majeſty with ſome good News.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Quite otherwiſe, <hi>Sycophante;</hi> I know not whether my Face belie my Heart, but I was never more Melancholy than now. Prithee ſing me that Song you learnt laſt, I like the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour on't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syc.</speaker>
                     <p>O my Conſcience ſo do I, for I put it in practice <stage>[aſide.</stage> but laſt Night.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Syc.</hi> ſings.</stage>
                     <lg>
                        <l>WHy ſhould Beauty ſtand conteſting</l>
                        <l>
                           <label>SONG.</label>With the amorous preſſing Lover,</l>
                        <l>When the granting of the bleſſing</l>
                        <l>To her ſelf new Joys diſcovers?</l>
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:151096:9"/>
                        <l>Let the Old and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>gly plead</l>
                        <l>Their Fears and vain Excuſes,</l>
                        <l>Beauty ſtands in no ſuch need,</l>
                        <l>And is above Abuſes.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="Cho.">
                        <l>
                           <hi>Yield</hi> Phyllis <hi>then while time invites,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And all your hopes are eaſie,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Delay in buſineſs or delights</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Should never never pleaſe you.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Delay in Buſineſs or Delights</l>
                     <l>Should never never pleaſe you.</l>
                     <l>Seaſonable advice, <hi>Sycophante,</hi> is it not?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syc.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, Madam, If a Body had the Will to follow it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah <hi>Sycophante,</hi> never tax my Will,</l>
                     <l>But blame that cruel over-ruling Fate,</l>
                     <l>That with an envious Induſtry oppoſes,</l>
                     <l>And bars the Progreſs of my Undertakings.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syc.</speaker>
                     <l>The Wiſe do always govern their own Fate,</l>
                     <l>And Fortune with officious Zeal attends</l>
                     <l>To crown their Enterprizes with Succeſs;</l>
                     <l>But ſince our Holy Prophet has been pleas'd</l>
                     <l>(Wiſely foreſeeing how your pious Care</l>
                     <l>Would ſerve to re-inſtate and to improve</l>
                     <l>The falling Intereſt of his juſt Diſciples)</l>
                     <l>To fix your Majeſty in this high Sphere,</l>
                     <l>The better to enable and enlarge</l>
                     <l>Thoſe Holy Reſolutions you had taken:</l>
                     <l>It would be now a ſort of Blaſphemy</l>
                     <l>Once to ſuſpect or doubt his juſt aſſiſtance.</l>
                     <l>No, No, great Princeſs, let but your endeavours</l>
                     <l>Go on with equal Zeal and Induſtry,</l>
                     <l>And I'll engage Perfection to your Wiſhes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:151096:9"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Remarquo <hi>at a diſtance.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Hum! Who have we got here now? On my life <stage>
                           <hi>[aſide.</hi> 
                        </stage> her pious Majeſty, with her brace of Counſellors; I'll warrant you they have no leſs buſineſs before them than building of Churches: Well, I muſt hearken, for by their whiſpering and caballing they muſt have ſome grand deſign on foot.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis true, I have it ſetled in my Heart,</l>
                     <l>From whence the torturing Rack ſhould never tear it,</l>
                     <l>During the time our holy Prophet grants</l>
                     <l>To us to ſhare and fill th'<hi>Hungarian</hi> Throne,</l>
                     <l>No means, endeavours, induſtry ſhall fail,</l>
                     <l>To extirpate the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Intereſt hence,</l>
                     <l>And raiſe the <hi>Pagans</hi> to their former Glory.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Why look ye there, what an even gueſs have I! I was ſure Religion was the main point in Debate: Theſe Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are never without a ſcruple of Conſcience, though they always take care to have the ſatisfaction of committing the Sin, before ever they'll put themſelves to the trouble of diſputing the Unlawfulneſs of it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
                     <l>Since then your Majeſty ſtands ſo reſolv'd,</l>
                     <l>(As 'tis high reaſon that you ſhould be ſo)</l>
                     <l>What can theſe doubts or needleſs ſcruples mean?</l>
                     <l>(Forgive me if my hearty Zeal provoke</l>
                     <l>Words which my conſcious Duty ſhould forbear)</l>
                     <l>Have you not now within your power to act</l>
                     <l>As even your Will ſhall prompt you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>No, <hi>Mazato,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The obſtinate <hi>Hungarians</hi> often plead</l>
                     <l>Peculiar Laws and antient Liberties,</l>
                     <l>Which with a daring reſolution they</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Lives and Fortunes</hi> threaten to defend.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
                     <l>Prerogative and Kingly Power runs low,</l>
                     <l>When 'tis diſputed by unthinking crowds,</l>
                     <l>Or which is worſe, by haughty Sanhedrims.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:151096:10"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Now ſhall we have theſe two Ladies new <stage>[aſide</stage> mould that Covernment in a moment, which has been ſetled by the wiſeſt Heads in the Kingdom for theſe hundred and fifty years.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
                     <l>But, Madam, grant this wild unruly Rabble</l>
                     <l>Should in a puling Fit repine or murmur,</l>
                     <l>Are we ſo deſtitute of ſound advice,</l>
                     <l>Of wilely Stratagems and Policies,</l>
                     <l>As we ſhould doubt to take this ſtalking Bug-bear,</l>
                     <l>Even in their own weak Snares?</l>
                     <l>Your <hi>Cullidada</hi>'s Predeceſſor knew</l>
                     <l>So well to manage even the moſt refin'd</l>
                     <l>Of all the Chriſtian Herd, that ſingly he</l>
                     <l>Would with his Eloquence alone defeat</l>
                     <l>The united Counſels of whole Sanhedrims.</l>
                     <l>'Tis known, the <hi>Mufti,</hi> our moſt Holy Father,</l>
                     <l>Has in his ſecret Conclave oft declar'd,</l>
                     <l>(According to our Prophets great Inſtructions,</l>
                     <l>As he is pleas'd to Interpret)</l>
                     <l>That for to propagate the Faith and Power,</l>
                     <l>Or to enlarge the ſacred Territories</l>
                     <l>Of his moſt pious <hi>Muſſulmen</hi>—No means,</l>
                     <l>Whether by breach of <hi>Oath,</hi> (which <hi>ſilly</hi> Chriſtians</l>
                     <l>Account ſo ſacred) or by the rougher Art</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Cutting Throats,</hi> of <hi>Poyſon, Halter, Dagger,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or any other yet unthought of way:</l>
                     <l>No means, I ſay, though ſeeming barbarous,</l>
                     <l>But what by ſtrict Anathema's declar'd</l>
                     <l>To be both good and meritorious.</l>
                     <l>And how can Royal <hi>Cullidada</hi> then,</l>
                     <l>Who by eſtabliſh'd great Prerogative</l>
                     <l>Has, like another Deity, the Power</l>
                     <l>Of Life and Death inveſted in himſelf;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>(For, whom the King's reſolved to ruine, who ſhall ſave?)</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>How can he want, let him but have the Will,</l>
                     <l>Means to compleat your utmoſt Reſolution?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:151096:10"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <stage>[aſide.]</stage>
                     <p>Now I ſhould never have wonder'd to have heard ſo learnd an Harangue from <hi>Barbaroſſa</hi> or <hi>Pietro,</hi> the two <hi>pious</hi> Directors of our gracious King's Conſcience; but from Madam <hi>Mazato</hi> this, whoſe whole Diſcourſe I thought ſhould have been of nothing but <hi>Billet Deux,</hi> and bawdy aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; indeed 'tis ſomething ſtrange! but I ſee Love-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues improve a body in State-politicks, as Soulders learn the Art of War by moving and removing the Men on a Cheſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board. Well, good People of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> if ever you deſire to be inform'd, or are willing to be perſwaded to turn <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometans,</hi> pray repair to Madam <hi>Mazato,</hi> and her Highneſs the Queen, they have <hi>forcible</hi> Arguments to induce you, and if you can prevail with your <hi>weak</hi> Stomachs to digeſt Haltar and Fagot, they have a <hi>flaming</hi> Zeal to convert you.</p>
                     <stage>[aſide.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas! <hi>Mazato, Cullidada</hi>'s Will,</l>
                     <l>After ſuch ſignal proofs can ne're be doubted;</l>
                     <l>His early Care and watchful Induſtry,</l>
                     <l>To re-induce our holy Alchoran,</l>
                     <l>Has even to danger of his Crown and Life,</l>
                     <l>Made him obnoxious to the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Laws:</l>
                     <l>Nor has the Acceſſion to the Imperial Crown</l>
                     <l>Allay'd or cool'd his firſt determinations:</l>
                     <l>But when by indefatigable Care,</l>
                     <l>By <hi>private Promiſes</hi> and <hi>publick Threats,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>By condeſcending Smiles and <hi>Cloſettings,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>By <hi>Judges pick'd,</hi> and <hi>penſion Sanhedrims;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>By private Murthers, publick Executions;</l>
                     <l>(For Obſtacles muſt be removed of courſe)</l>
                     <l>By breach of Words, and often Perjuries;</l>
                     <l>When by theſe means and others, dear <hi>Mazato,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>We have ſhak'd the ſure Foundations of thoſe Laws,</l>
                     <l>Which the <hi>Hungarians</hi> ſo much boaſt and value;</l>
                     <l>The momentary pleaſures we ſhall reap,</l>
                     <l>Will prove no more ſubſtantial than the Dreams</l>
                     <l>Of Thirſty Drunkards —</l>
                     <l>Alaſs, <hi>Mazato,</hi> one bold ſtroke of Time</l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:151096:11"/>
                     <l>Or Death, can in one moment diſannul</l>
                     <l>All that our tedious Induſtry has gain'd,</l>
                     <l>And then how ſoon that fatal ſtroke may happen</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Cullidada</hi>'s growing Weakneſſes</l>
                     <l>(Which like the ſilent ſteps of Midnight Thieves</l>
                     <l>Creep hourly on him) we have much more cauſe</l>
                     <l>To fear, than hopes to hinder:</l>
                     <stage>Mazato <hi>ſtarts</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Well may'ſt thou ſtart to hear theſe frightful Truths.</l>
                     <l>But what muſt I, <hi>Mazato,</hi> who muſt ſtand</l>
                     <l>And bear the teſt of all; unleſs kind Fate</l>
                     <l>And our wiſe <hi>Mufti</hi> could inculcate to us</l>
                     <l>Some more effectual Method to ſecure</l>
                     <l>Our Infant Projects to <hi>Poſterity?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Mazato <hi>ſhakes her head, and muſes.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syc.</speaker>
                     <p>Now if a body might ſpeak plain truth to her Majeſty, what a hopeful way could I put her in, and cure her of all fears and ſcruples?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>What truth thou canſt ſpeak in this matter, <hi>Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phante,</hi> relates to the good of the Publick, and therefore can't diſpleaſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syc.</speaker>
                     <p>Then, Madam, with ſubmiſſion, I'de have you do as ſeveral of your wiſe Predeceſſors have done before. I have read of ſome notable Queens of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> as well as of other neighbouring Countries, who when their Husbands have been troubled with the Pip, like old Cocks that have loſt their ſpurs, or their thoughts ſo taken up with abſtract notions of Divinity, that they have had no leiſure to mind even the neceſſary carnal Affairs of the World; why then, mark me, theſe Queens fearing to loſe the opportunity of having their Pictures drawn, (for that's the way that Queens tranſmit their memory to poſterity) they have ſat ſeveral times to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Limners, and ſo continu'd 'till the buſineſs has been done to the Life. Now, Madam, though I confeſs <hi>Cullidada</hi> has been a reputed good Painter in his time, yet now he's grown old, and his Hand ſhakes, his Pencil is worn, and his Eyes are bad, his Fancy pall'd, and his Colours corrupt, ſo that you
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151096:11"/>may better ſit to a Sign-poſt dawber than to him; therefore Madam I adviſe you to ſend quickly for ſome of the moſt expert in the Trade; be aſſiduous and diligent; for hang me, I never grudg'd my pains ſo I could gain my ends; and in a very ſhort time you'll find a happy alteration in your Affairs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Why thou art a rare diſcuſſer of hard Queſtions <hi>Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phante;</hi> thou argueſt like a Philoſopher.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syc.</speaker>
                     <p>I pretend to be part of a Natural one.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>But the greateſt difficulty is, to find ſome of theſe Artiſts; I know but few, and a body would not truſt to ſtrangers: They are often careleſs or ignorant; and I would not have my Buſineſs ſlubber'd over.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, now I hope to come in with a piece of Advice: If your Majeſty would have your Buſineſs done exactly, and to the very life, Take my <hi>Tommy;</hi> well he has a bold ſtroak with him; he draws all in Fleſh and Blood: <hi>Tommy,</hi> Madam, <hi>Tommy</hi> ſhould be the Man, I ſay: Though by the way, I had rather ſhe'd let him alone; for my <hi>Tommy</hi> has as much buſineſs with me as he can lay his hand to. <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>No <hi>Mazato,</hi> I ſhould not like thy <hi>Tommy:</hi> He has been a long time about thee, and yet has made but a bare piece of work on't. Now Vengeance take them, if they don't gueſs bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſave me the trouble of naming one my ſelf. Oh! Dear <hi>Dadamore,</hi> haſt thou never a Friend here?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syc.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll name your Majeſty ſeveral, and ſo take their choice. What think you of <hi>Pietro?</hi> Let me tell you he has a gentile way with him, to my knowledge.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis true, I could fancy <hi>Pietro</hi> well enough for an after Game;</p>
                     <stage>[aſide]</stage>
                     <p>and indeed, for fear of the worſt, a body would have two ſtrings to ones Bow: But my Count, my Count; in Drawing, Fancy is a vaſt matter: Oh, if I were to be drawn in Fleſh and Blood, (as <hi>Mazato</hi> ſays) my Count would be the Man.</p>
                     <stage>[Aſide.]</stage>
                     <p>No <hi>Sycophante, Pietro</hi>'s a devout Man, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the Church; he might miſtake my Minutes, and fall a Preaching up Abſtinence when I have a mind to Feaſt. No <hi>Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phante,</hi> I would be upon ſure grounds; you know I have been baulkt enough already: Oh! My dear <hi>Dadamore.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:151096:12"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syc.</speaker>
                     <p>I find her drift:</p>
                     <stage>[Aſide]</stage>
                     <p>'Tis certain our <hi>Hungarians</hi> are not ſo lively and brisk in their Fancies, as your <hi>Gallo Graecians</hi> and <hi>Italians.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! Your <hi>Italians</hi> are brave Fellows; why they are Men of an univerſal fancy; there's not Man, Woman, Beaſt or Fowl, ſcapes them: Nay, I have heard them ſay, the great <hi>Noah</hi> was an <hi>Italian,</hi> and that moſt of the Creatures in the Ark were of his own drawing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syc.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then I have thought of an <hi>Italian</hi> that will fit your Majeſty to an Hairs breadth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Who prithee <hi>Sycophante?</hi> Who? Prithee name him my Dear: Who? Who? <stage>[ſhe makes up eagerly]</stage> Oh! if ſhe ſhould miſtake me now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syc.</speaker>
                     <p>I hope I need go no farther than the Noble Count <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damore.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Remarquo <hi>liſtens, and retires to a corner.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! <hi>Sycophante</hi> thou haſt touch'd the ſtring that makes Harmonious Muſick in my Soul.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syc.</speaker>
                     <p>Now this comes of Modeſty: If you had ſpoke but half a word of this before, your buſineſs had been done by this, but ſince it is as it is, better late than never.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Since all our Intereſts are ſo interwoven,</l>
                     <l>Why ſhould I doubt to tell you my reſolves?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pietro, Dadamore,</hi> and you my Friends,</l>
                     <l>Do all agree that nothing but an Heir</l>
                     <l>Can fully raiſe and fix our juſt deſires:</l>
                     <l>Nay, even <hi>Cullidada</hi> does agree</l>
                     <l>In this, and differs only in the Manner.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Mufti</hi> will aſſiſt in this juſt Cauſe,</l>
                     <l>Our Neighbour Monarch preſſes it with Zeal:</l>
                     <l>Time, Circumſtance, and Sacred Duty urge us,</l>
                     <l>And ſhall we now be backward to our ſelves?</l>
                     <l>'Tis true, ſince neceſſity does urge,</l>
                     <l>My <hi>Dadamore</hi> of all Men elſe I'd chooſe;</l>
                     <l>And my Prophetick Soul foretold ſucceſs,</l>
                     <l>Even from the lucky minute of his Landing.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For then alone our Hopes do fairest ſtand,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>When Love goes with Religion hand in hand.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Exeunt Omnes.]</stage>
               </div>
               <trailer>The End of the firſt ACT.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:151096:12"/>
               <head>ACT II.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Remarquo <hi>ſolus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>SO ſo! we are like to have warm work on't e'faith; this late Scene of Mirth and Joy for our new King and Queen may probably prove like the laſt blaze of a Candle ſpent in the ſocket: Young <hi>Philodemus</hi> they ſay is Landed in the Weſt with a truſty Troop of <hi>Myrmidons,</hi> and ſets up for the Chriſtian Religion: Ha, ha, this Religion is the moſt quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome thing in the World. There has not been a War in <hi>Europe</hi> this many Ages, but Religion ſtill came in for a ſhare; and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven knows, they that make moſt pother about it have commonly leaſt to do with it: Well, what the event may be I cannot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; but it is certain, this young Prince carries a great ſtroke in the Peoples Hearts, though in reality, he is but Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Son to the late King; and has no more right to the Crown of <hi>Hungary,</hi> than I have to be King of <hi>Poland;</hi> however this good may come of his Enterprize, that if he eſcapes, though he be vanquiſhed, he'll ſerve for a bridle to the exorbitant humour of our haughty ill-deſigning Queen, and to correct the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of an obſtinate bigotted King. I have heard part of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns; and how to advance the <hi>Pagan</hi> Religion in <hi>Hungary,</hi> ſhe would not ſcruple to expoſe her Husbands Honour, her own Chaſtity, or the Kingdoms Welfare and Peace; but let her drive on, I have a reſerve in ſtore for her, that will make her Minions ſcratch, her ſelf chafe, and <hi>Cullidada</hi> tremble; that will make him turn his tune of Obedience without <hi>Reſerve,</hi> and be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151096:13"/>glad if his People will then take their own again and be quiet: But ſtay, here he comes with his <hi>Pious</hi> Chancellor and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor; he has Fire in his Eyes, and ſullen Rage in his Face; he has heard of <hi>Monumora</hi>'s Landing: I'll huſh, up in a corner, and hear their Conference.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> King, Barbaroſſa, Pietro, Philanax, <hi>with Guards and Attendance.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, 'tis no more than what he has threatned, and I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; but what numbers has he with him?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis certain he brought not an hundred with him, but in two days he's increaſed to three thouſand, you may ſee now the Faith and Loyalty of Chriſtians.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pietro,</hi> abuſe not the principle of Chriſtianity, for the evil practices of a few miſguided Creatures.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſpeak very tenderly of them <hi>Philanax,</hi> thou ſeemeſt unwilling to call them what they are, <hi>Rebels.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, from this time forward farewel Chriſtianity; they ſhall loſe a Pillar of me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <stage>[Aſide]</stage>
                     <p>O my Conſcience, a Caterpillar both in Church and State.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Well I ſhall have the handling of ſome of them, I'll put a Collar mark on them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <p>Have you given Orders for raiſing the Militia? What Troops are gone down? Detach half of my own Guards, and make what haſte you can to meet them: I hear they talk big, I'll ſoon try whether Rebels Hearts are as good as their Tongues.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>Do you hear <hi>Philanax,</hi> the King ſays you muſt give no quarter: Sir, <stage>[he whiſpers the King,]</stage> you may lop them off now with Conſcience and Honour, (as they have it in their Language) all that are in Arms ſhall fall of courſe, and <hi>Barbaroſſa,</hi> by a fetch of Law, will bring in the reſt for Abettors.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, nay, I reckon I ſhall come in for the gleanings: Well my Teeth water to be amongſt them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:151096:13"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Meſſenger.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>God Save our Sovereign Lord the King.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee tell me of ſaving when the Enemy's beat. What News from the Rebels?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>Why an't pleaſe your Majeſty, they are all there toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee where together, how many are they, what do they do, and where's my Army? Speak to all this.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then an't pleaſe your Majeſty, they are like a ſwarm of Bees; I'll warrant you they are at leaſt a Thouſand: No, no, I miſtake, they are more a huge deal; for I ſaw them, and they reach'd from one end of our great Lane to th'other, and they all ſwore, they'd fight up to the Ears in Blood for the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan Religion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Exit</hi> Meſſenger.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This is the Chriſtian Paſſive Obedience, Sir.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, yes, when they want an opportunity to get into Active Rebellion, why then they are all for Paſſive Obedience: But let but ſome fawning Nobleman, that can pull off his Hat to the Rabble, and ſhake hands with the Country Gentry at a Horſe Race; let him I ſay but repair to the Market-Croſs of ſome diſaffected Town, and make an harangue of <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Propery,</hi> and the Chriſtian Religion, and e'faith they'll change their Tune in a moment, and like negligent School-boys when they have got into a new Leſſon, they preſently forget the old one.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <p>Well <hi>Pietro,</hi> when this bruſh is over, I'll read 'em a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of <hi>Pagan</hi> inſtruction:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>And I'll ſee them put it in practice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, let not ill inſinuating Tongues,</l>
                     <l>So far prevail upon your Royal Heart,</l>
                     <l>To make you think your Chriſtians can be falſe.</l>
                     <l>I ſaw your Troops when marching 'gainſt your Foe;</l>
                     <l>And ſaw on every Face the ſtamps of Loyalty.</l>
                     <l>Such vigorous briskneſs in their Eyes was ſeen,</l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:151096:14"/>
                     <l>As when the Bridegroom haſtens to his Joys:</l>
                     <l>And as they march'd and turn'd through every ſtreet,</l>
                     <l>In loud and oft repeated Acclamations,</l>
                     <l>They cry'd, (which by the joyful People was return'd)</l>
                     <l>Let our great <hi>Cullidada</hi> Live and Reign,</l>
                     <l>And let his Rebels periſh.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <p>Well <hi>Philanax,</hi> I know thou ſpeakſt thy Love; but late experience, to my coſt, has ſhewn your Chriſtians love and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Sir, they ſhew'd their Zealous Loyalty, when with unheard of Impudence they ſtood diſputing your <hi>Succeſſion</hi> to the Throne.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, yes Sir, do but truſt them as your Father did, and they'll make you a <hi>Glorious</hi> Prince: Sir <hi>Philanax,</hi> you do ill I muſt tell, to plead thus for a company of Rebels; let me tell you Sir, I have had many a one <hi>Whipt and Fined unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi> for leſs words than theſe: Come Sir let's have no pleading for Rebels.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, when I plead 'tis for the innocent, and let the guilty ſuffer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, guilty or innocent, 'tis all one for that; if the King has a mind to puniſh them, 'tis <hi>ill Manners</hi> to argue againſt it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir I am ſilent. O! Poor <hi>Hungaria,</hi> thou art like to thrive under ſuch a diſpenſer of Juſtice.</p>
                     <stage>[Aſide.]</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Phil.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter ſecond</hi> Meſſenger.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>Great Sir, the Enemy in a vaſt Body are on their march, and deſign, without delay, for <hi>Alba Regalis.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <p>How far's our Army from them?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>Seven Leagues.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pietro</hi> then make haſte, ſend to our General;</l>
                     <l>Bid him, with all the ſpeed he can, advance</l>
                     <l>And give them Battle: We muſt ſtop their progreſs,</l>
                     <l>Or they'll gather like a rowling Snow-ball.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Ex.</hi> Pie. Meſſ.</stage>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:151096:14"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Barbaroſſa</hi> you muſt alſo ſpeed,</l>
                     <l>And prepare a Proclamation of Pardon</l>
                     <l>To all that ſhall return to their Duty</l>
                     <l>Within five days.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I muſt for ſhow put on the meek Lambs skin,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But ſoon they'll feell I'me Lyon all within.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Ex</hi> K. Bar.</stage>
                  <stage>Manet</stage>
                  <stage>Remarquo <hi>ſolus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Certainly never Man took ſuch pains to win a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as this unhappy Prince does to loſe one: He has taken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to be the Father of his People; yet has ſworn in his Heart to ruine and deſtroy them: He has Apoſtatized from his Faith, and made a <hi>ſale of his Honour;</hi> and as it was ſaid of him before his coming to the Crown That he never broke his word: So ſince his acceſſion we may ſay, to our ſorrow, That he never kept it. His people ſet him up, though excluded by Law, and choſe rather to be guided by their love to his Family, than by the reaſonable Rules of even neceſſary Politicks; they generouſly fixed all their thoughts on the King, and never diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted the Errours of the <hi>Pagan;</hi> and how well they are likely to be paid for their kindneſs, the <hi>Queen</hi> and <hi>Pietro</hi> have too late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared. Well, they may be as extravagant as they pleaſe, but 'e fack the Reckoning muſt be paid one day.</p>
                     <l>Sure-footed Vengeance, though he moves not faſt,</l>
                     <l>Will catch th' unwary Criminal at laſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Ex</hi> Remarq.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:151096:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SCENE II.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Monumora</hi>'s Out-Guards.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Country-Man.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Firſt <hi>Centinel.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Who comes there, ſtand, what are you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Countryman.</speaker>
                     <p>A poor Countryman that has left his Wife and ſeven Children, to come and fight with his Highneſſes Grace for the Churſten Religion, God bleſs him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cent.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee ſpeak, are you for the Chriſtian Duke of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numora,</hi> or the Pagan King of <hi>Hungaria?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Countr.</speaker>
                     <p>Udsbud he would fight for ne'r a Pagan King in <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom,</hi> ſo he would'nt, as long as he could heave a Bill to his Shoulders: No, no, he would have no ſaying Prayers to the <hi>Twelve Apoſtles,</hi> and twenty more beſide. No, no, the good Wife would never let'n live in quiet, if I dud'nt fight for Prince <hi>Philodemy</hi> and the Churſten Religion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cent.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou art one of us I ſee, come on; what Arms haſt thou brought with thee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                     <p>Slid h' has both Arms and Ammunition; Law ye, here's a good tough brown Bill, and the beſt white Loaf <hi>Joan</hi> e'r made in all her Life.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cent.</speaker>
                     <p>That's one ſort of Ammunition indeed: Come honeſt Brother, paſs; you are in the direct way to the Main-Guard, and ſo good morrow.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter ſecond</hi> Countryman.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cent.</speaker>
                     <p>Who comes there? ſtand, ſtand or I'll fire, ſtand I ſay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                     <p>What a Fool he was to make a Maun ſtand tull the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Rogues come and knockn o'the head: Udsbud ler'n go to the Churſten Camp, and help young <hi>Philodemy</hi> to thraſh thoſe Pagan Dogs: A murrain on 'em hoo can't abide 'um.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cent.</speaker>
                     <p>Advance, advance Brother; what Arms have you brought with you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:151096:15"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>By my faith Maun as good a Scith as e'r mov'd Hay; udsbud hoo wull ſo maule their ſhanks, hoo wull warrant the Pagan Rogues for coming into the Weſt Country theſe twonty Years again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cent.</speaker>
                     <p>Well Brother you know the way, I wiſh you a good Joruney.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter a</hi> Country Maid <hi>crying and running.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <p>Alack, alack, my poor <hi>Jonny;</hi> alack, alack, why wud he go to be kill'd by the ugly Pagans.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cent.</speaker>
                     <p>Hey day what have we hear, a young Dove that has loſt her Mate, and now ſhe's a cooing after him. Well what want you, whether are you travelling ſo early.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>Alack, did hoo ſee my poor <hi>Jonny</hi> away here?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cent.</speaker>
                     <p>What a like man was he?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>Ah hoo's <hi>Jonny</hi> was aruddy like Maun, and hoo told me, hoo lov'd me dearly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cent.</speaker>
                     <p>Come give me a good kiſs, and I'll—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>While the</hi> Centinel <hi>offers to kiſs the Maid, Trumpets ſound, and Drums beat; at which he ſtarts</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cent.</speaker>
                     <p>Troop off. troop off, my little Doxy, <hi>Mars</hi> cannot be in Conjunction with <hi>Venus,</hi> this time.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Drums and Trumpets again. Enter</hi> Philodemus, <hi>Officers and Souldiers on one ſide, the Rable on the other.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Firſt of the <hi>Rabble.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Look, look, do's hoo ſee? Which is Prince <hi>Philodemy?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Second.</speaker>
                     <p>Why you tall Maun with the Noſe: Oh! Hoo's ſo like his Father.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Third.</speaker>
                     <p>Why did hoo's know his Father?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Second.</speaker>
                     <p>No, know'n what then, hoo's ſure he muſt be like his Father he's ſo handſome.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                     <p>Gentlemen, keep ſilence while the Prince ſpeaks.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[The Prince beckens with his Hand, and pulls of his Hat</stage>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:151096:16"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Philod.</speaker>
                     <p>Gentlemen,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Firſt <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Did ever hoo hear ſuch a civil, well bred Prince; why hoo call'd us all Gentlemen at the very firſt word: Well, hoo ſhall have my Vote to be King.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Philod.</speaker>
                     <p>I am come here to fight for the Chriſtian Religion; and I hope you'll all ſtick by me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, yes, we'll all fight for the Churſten Religion, and Prince <hi>Philodemy.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Philod.</speaker>
                     <p>Do ye love your Wives?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rab.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, yes, we love our Wives as long as we can ſtand.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Firſt <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>No, no, I don't love my Wife; for I caught her a mowing with <hi>Jacob</hi> in the Barn, ſo I don't love my Wife, but I love the Churſten Religion and young <hi>Philodemy.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Philod</speaker>
                     <p>And you would not have them taken away and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed by the cruel Pagans.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>Udsbud, No, hoo's have many a broken head firſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Second <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Udsfiſh an they raviſh my Wife, hoo would <hi>ſub poena</hi> 'm into the Biſhops Court, and let'n take what follows.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Philod.</speaker>
                     <p>And you would not have your Children murthered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your Faces?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>Ah lack, no no.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[here they fall a wouling.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fourth. <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Alack, I would not have my <hi>Tommy</hi> kill'd for the beſt Cow in my Landlords ſtall; ah Neighbour, you know his God mother would almoſt cry her Eyes out for him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Philod.</speaker>
                     <p>Well Gentlemen, if you have a value for your Wives, your Children and Eſtates; if you wiſh well to the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as Eſtabliſh'd by Law; if you would keep your Churches undefiled with the Heatheniſh Idolatry of the Pagans, and your Daughters with their Beaſtly Luſts; why then Gentlemen ſtick cloſe by me, and I ſhall endeavour to preſerve you in your Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, your Laws, your Liberties, and over and above reward every one of you for your kindneſs and love to me: Therefore Gentlemen, if you do reſolve to eſpouſe this Cauſe with me, let us be reſolute and valiant, and oppoſe our Enemies to the utmoſt drop of our Blood: We ſhall not have many of theſe opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities to do our ſelves good, therefore we muſt ſtrike now or
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151096:16"/>never; and indeed if we gain this, we need fear no more, our Enemies will never ſtand again, no they will run like Hares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Firſt <hi>Rable,</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Run away ſays he? Will they ſo? Udsbud then I'll be after them full drive; I always lov'd an Enemy that would run away without any more ado: Oh! I fight like a Lyon always when they run away.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Philod.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray Gentlemen bring what Fire Arms you can with you, and I'll take care to have you Regimented and well diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and ſo I bid you heartily farewel.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Second <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>But heark you me, I pray your <stage>[the D. is going.</stage> Worſhip one word with you before you go.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Philod.</speaker>
                     <p>Speak Friend.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rab.</speaker>
                     <p>Mun we be all Officers?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Offic.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! yes, yes, all Officers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Ex. D. cum ſuis.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Third <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Why then heark you me neighbour, I'll be a Collonel; and look ye me, becauſe you are my friend, you ſhall be, <stage>[he ſcratches]</stage> what do'n you call that is the next Maun af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter me,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fourth <hi>Rob.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Pugh, pugh, I'll be the place of a Juſtice, law ye now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fifth <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Why hoo's a Fool, we mu'n be all Collonels or Captains; why there never is any <hi>Iuſtice</hi> in the Kings Army:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sixth <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Come, come, lets us make our ſelves ready for theſe Pagan Rogues, and ſo let us pray, <stage>[ownes]</stage> God bleſs the Churſten Religion and Prince <hi>Philodemy.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Exeum Rable.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SCENE III.</hi> The Scene changes to <hi>Alba Regalis.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Barbaroſſa, Pietro</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>No News from the Camp yet <hi>Pietro.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie,</speaker>
                     <p>The King has not a word but that the Rebels increaſe dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: He has ſent other ſtrict orders to the General to fight them without delay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:151096:17"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Remarquo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>'Twas a deſperate attempt of the Duke of <hi>Monumora</hi>'s to invade a Kingdom at time of peace with ſo ſmall a handful of Men.</p>
                     <p>He had certainly great hopes of Friends in the Country, and I begin to fear the worſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, you and I muſt follow the ſame fate; we muſt ſtick cloſe together.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>I hope to ſee you cloſe hang together. <stage>[aſide.]</stage>
                     </p>
                     <p>My Lord your Servant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Honeſt <hi>Remarquo</hi> how goes it: Well I have conſidred your affair, and deſign you a kindneſs aſſoon as this Plaugy buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Weſt is over.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>R.</speaker>
                     <p>My good Lord, your Servant thanks you; perhaps his own buſineſs may be over by that time.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>Well <hi>Remarquo</hi> what News from the Rebels; I have not been at Court to day.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Now will I heat 'um: <stage>[aſide]</stage> Why Sir, matters appear to be much more dangerous than we thought at firſt: The Country comes in ſtrangely to them; they all cry up for the Churſten Religion, and Prince <hi>Philodemus,</hi> whom they now call King.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Barbaroſſa <hi>ſtartles.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B</speaker>
                     <p>Good lack <hi>Remarquo;</hi> but is it ſo?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>He has put out a Proclamation of Pardon to all that will ſubmit, with ſome few exceptions only; and I think he has had the Confidence to put in your Lordſhip and this Gentleman more for two.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Bar. <hi>fumes and muſes.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Udſlife this is very hard, to fall thus from the very prick of preferment; this muſt not be.</p>
                     <stage>[Aſide.]</stage>
                     <p>
                        <stage>[<hi>He muſes and looks hard at</hi> Pietro.]</stage> And is the Reverend <hi>Pietro.</hi> excepted too, 'tis unjuſt: Let me ſee, I muſt contrive ſome way or other to ſave my bacon; <stage>[aſide]</stage> what if I ſhould betray <hi>Pietro</hi> into the Dukes hands: <stage>[aſide]</stage> Nay, King Queen, all ſhould go if I could ſave but <hi>Barbaroſſa,</hi> the great <hi>Barbaroſſa:</hi> I'd aſſoon hang as go to my old trade of Petryfogging again. <stage>[Aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:151096:17"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Meſſenger.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord the King commands both your attendance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Ex</hi> Barb. Piet.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! The tortures of a guilty Conſcience.</l>
                     <l>See how he fum'd and trembled at my News:</l>
                     <l>The ſound of a Poſt-boys horn's as trobleſom</l>
                     <l>To him as that of a Paſſing-Bell:</l>
                     <l>And there's not a Meſſenger comes from the Camp,</l>
                     <l>But he fancies he has a preſent of a Halter to make him.</l>
                     <l>Well, he has been the boldeſt Sinner that ever <hi>Hungary</hi> knew:</l>
                     <p>For whereas moſt Vices covet to lurk under the diſguiſe of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, he has made it his ſole buſineſs to expoſe his bare faced; as if it was not ſufficient for the World to <hi>know,</hi> without they <hi>ſaw</hi> him commit them.</p>
                     <l>Yes <hi>Barbaroſſa</hi> I will do this right,</l>
                     <l>What e'r thou art, thou art no <hi>Hypocrite.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Ex</hi> Remarque</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Scene the</hi> Camps.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter the Duke of</hi> Monumora, <hi>leading his Army over the Stage.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                     <p>Halt; give the Word ſoftly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
                     <p>Halt, halt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <p>Gentlemen we muſt march with all the ſilence imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; the Night favours us, and we may take them knapping. When we come upon them, we muſt fall on without any good morrows; one hours good work and the day is our own: Bill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſucceed the Shot, and fall on pell mell; 'twill be time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to give Quarter at Sun-riſe, when we can know who and who's together. Now march.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
                     <p>March, march</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:151096:18"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Noiſe of Drums, Trumpets, ſhouts, cryes of Dying Men, claſhing of Swords,</hi> &amp;c</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Officer <hi>with</hi> Souldiers <hi>re-treating.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Offi.</speaker>
                     <p>Stand, ſtand, and charge the Rogues; ſome Villian betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us; they were prepared for us: Come, come, charge; flying wont ſave us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[They beat the Enemy back</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Duke of</hi> Monumora.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Here Collonel, take your Regiment of Firelocks; line thoſe Hedges; I'll ſtand the Body. Where's the Horſe? Here ſpeed to the Horſe, bid them charge their Flanks: Charge them home brave boys. They fly, they fly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[They beat the Enemy off again.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Soldier.</stage>
                  <p>Sir provide for your ſelf: Retreat aſſoon as you can; you are betrayed: The General of the Horſe is march'd off without ſtriking a ſtroak: The Enemy are pouring in upon us, and 'twill be impoſſible to ſtand.</p>
                  <stage>[The Duke ſtands amazed.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Offic.</speaker>
                     <p>Dear Sir make off, you'll be ſurrounded in a moment.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <l>VVe have time enough to damn that Villian firſt,</l>
                     <l>Let him by <hi>Woman, Man,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> be curſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex</hi> Duke</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Drums, Trumpets, Shouts Acclamations of Victory Enter a few Soulders of the</hi> Dukes, <hi>crying Quarter, Quarter, Purſued by Officer and Souldiers</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Offi.</speaker>
                     <p>Down with them, down with the Rebels.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Quarter, Quarter, Noble Collonel, ſpare our Lives.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Offi.</speaker>
                     <p>Down with your Arms then, <stage>[They through them down]</stage> though you had as good be knock'd o'the head as hang'd. Here takes the Rogues, tye them together, and drive'um before you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Souldier, Tye um.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sol.</speaker>
                     <p>Come march you Rebelly Dogs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:151096:18"/>
                  <stage>Enter the Kings Army with Drums Beating, Colours flying, Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets ſounding, leading their Priſners with them: The General meets them.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>Gentlemen you have behaved your ſelves bravely; the King has ordered his Thanks to you, and will take care to reward you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Soldiers</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <stage>ſhout,</stage>
                        <hi>Long Live</hi> Culledada <hi>King of</hi> Hungary.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>Here you Collonel, detach a Regiment of Horſe, and two of foot, and ſcowr about the adjacent Countries for <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora;</hi> he can't be got far; the King gives Five Hundred Pound to them that take him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Duke of</hi> Monumora</speaker>
                     <stage>ſolus in diſguiſe.</stage>
                     <l>And art thou then that Glorious <hi>Monumora?</hi> 
                        <stage>[looking on himſelf.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe Praiſe fill'd every Tongue, touch'd every Heart:</l>
                     <l>Whoſe beck commanded the obſequious croud;</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Name, (like that of <hi>Hannibal</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi>)</l>
                     <l>Did make the proud <hi>Hungarian</hi> Monarch tremble:</l>
                     <l>Sure thou miſtak'ſt thy ſelf, and by ſome trick</l>
                     <l>Of wild Enchantment, thou art here deluded.</l>
                     <l>Who waits there? No Attendance? Call my Guards,</l>
                     <l>How fares the Army? come lets charge the Flanck.</l>
                     <l>Bring up the Horſe: So ho! bring up the Horſe!</l>
                     <l>Now by the Gods the Villain flyes: Oh! See the Villian</l>
                     <l>Now <hi>Monumora</hi> thou haſt time to ſee</l>
                     <stage>[He groans.</stage>
                     <l>The ſlippery, weak Foundation of thy Greatneſs:</l>
                     <l>That Airy Phantome of a Diadem,</l>
                     <l>Which thou with ſo much eager fondneſs ſtrove.</l>
                     <l>To graſp, which coſt thee ſome whole toilſome Years,</l>
                     <l>That rob'd thee of thy Pleaſure all the day,</l>
                     <l>Thy Nights of Sleep and neceſſary Reſt:</l>
                     <l>Thou haſt ſeen it now in one poor minute vaniſh.</l>
                     <l>One Sun has ſeen thee riſe a hopeful Monarch.</l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:151096:19"/>
                     <l>And ſhew'd thee Mountains of ſolid Gold:</l>
                     <l>The next has with an envious hand withdrawn,</l>
                     <l>(As new ſueceeding Kings are wont to do)</l>
                     <l>All that his Predeceſſors gave before</l>
                     <l>Not yet five hours, and thou wer't great and good:</l>
                     <l>The Chriſtians Hope, the Pagans Four and Torror,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hungaria</hi>'s great Defender, King, and Darling:</l>
                     <l>Now, poor forſaken Caitiff, Villain Rebel.</l>
                     <l>Such Fortune is thy vaſt unlimited Power,</l>
                     <l>That canſt as 'twere unite even Contradictions.</l>
                     <l>In thee alone 'tis placed, to Carſe or Bleſs,</l>
                     <l>Nor Cauſe, nor Man, is good without ſucceſs.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <trailer>The End of the Second ACT.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>ACT. III.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I. Alba Regalis.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> King, Barbaroſſa, Pietro, Philanax.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>King.</speaker>
                     <l>WEll now Sir <hi>Philanax,</hi> I hope you'll grant,</l>
                     <l>Your Chriſtians can be Rebels, ſturdy Rebels:</l>
                     <l>Yes, yes, I am inform'd, though much o'r power'd,</l>
                     <l>By th' number of my Forces, yet they ſtood</l>
                     <l>And ſought it briskly. Sure they were inſpir'd</l>
                     <l>By their young <hi>Dagon.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:151096:19"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <l>When they firſt came on</l>
                     <l>In ecchoing Shouts, they thus expreſs'd themſelves,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Long Live</hi> Hungaria<hi>'s King, Great</hi> MONUMORA.</l>
                     <l>But your great General, who even from their Camp</l>
                     <l>Had early Notice of their dark Deſign,</l>
                     <l>Stood well prepar'd, and ready to receive</l>
                     <l>Their fierce Aſſault, and within two Hours ſpace</l>
                     <l>Quaſh'd and unravell'd all their long-laid Treaſon.</l>
                     <l>What yet remains, lies at your Royal Pleaſure;</l>
                     <l>That is, the Priſoners.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>If your Majeſty pleaſes to depute me for that Buſineſs, I have a <hi>Compendious</hi> way to deal with them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <p>Your's be the care of that, <hi>Barbaroſſa.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Now if I ſhould have a queaſie fit come upon me, and be Merciful, it would vex me heartily.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, thou wilt take as much pity of their Cries,</l>
                     <l>As a hungry Wolf does of the bleating Lambs.</l>
                     <stage>(Aſide.)</stage>
                     <l>Dread Soveraign,</l>
                     <l>May all your Enemies and Rebels periſh</l>
                     <l>As theſe have done, your Faithful Servant prays:</l>
                     <l>But, Royal Sir, forgive me if I wiſh</l>
                     <l>Your Majeſty were ſomething more acquainted</l>
                     <l>With the firm Loyalty and Principles</l>
                     <l>Of all your Chriſtians in general;</l>
                     <l>As they in number far exceed your Pagans,</l>
                     <l>So 'tis in Wealth the Sinews of all Power.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis that which troubles me, but I ſhall Level</l>
                     <l>And crop that monſtrous growth they ſo rely on:</l>
                     <l>Let them now flatter their rebellious hopes,</l>
                     <l>And find ſome other <hi>Monumora</hi> to ſet up,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>This</hi> they may give over:</l>
                     <l>I'll try how far my high Prerogative</l>
                     <l>Dare be diſputed by a crop-ſick Crowd;</l>
                     <l>I'll break the Curb of haughty <hi>Sanhedrim's,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who with audacious Arrogance would plead</l>
                     <l>And argue my juſt Favour to my Friends:</l>
                     <l>No, <hi>Philanax,</hi> it ſhall be ſo no more;</l>
                     <l>I'll ſet oppreſſed Vertue free.</l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:151096:20"/>
                     <l>And raiſe the <hi>Clouded</hi> Glory of my Pagans.</l>
                     <l>Their Loyalty to me is well aſſur'd:</l>
                     <l>Nay, I have try'd it in the worſt of times,</l>
                     <l>And I might well be call'd Ungenerous,</l>
                     <l>If for ſome dull Formalities of Law,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I ſhould expoſe to want or to diſgrace</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My Faithful'ſt Subjects, and my chiefeſt Friends.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Meſſenger.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Great Sir, your Noble General ſends to tell,</l>
                     <l>And to Congratulate your Majeſty,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Monumora</hi>'s taken.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Is he taken?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[in Amaz.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>Taken, and lurking in a poor Diſguiſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <l>I wiſh he had rather fallen in the Field.</l>
                     <l>But ſince 'tis ſo, Juſtice muſt have its courſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, if I had a ſtock of Pity now, I don't know but I might ſpare him a little; but hang it, he had better die, than <hi>Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidada,</hi> and the Kingdom ſhould loſe a good Chancellor.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(<hi>Ex.</hi> Meſſ.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <l>Great Sir, from this long Series of Succeſs,</l>
                     <l>We find our Holy Prophet favour us.</l>
                     <l>From hence I humbly move, he will exact</l>
                     <l>All the moſt ſuitable Returns of Zeal.</l>
                     <l>He has thro' dark and untrod ways of Danger</l>
                     <l>Convey'd you ſafely to the Imperial Throne,</l>
                     <l>Now by a great Deliverance from your Rebels,</l>
                     <l>Who like a ſwelling Torrent had broke looſe:</l>
                     <l>And but for this reſtraining Providence,</l>
                     <l>Had over-flown and ruin'd your whole Kingdom.</l>
                     <l>Your proud inſulting Enemy he has curb'd;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>An Enemy indeed,</hi> who dar'd to deſpiſe</l>
                     <l>Even our moſt Holy Faith and You.</l>
                     <l>Now, Royal Sir, 'tis left to you to improve</l>
                     <l>Theſe mighty Benefits he has beſtow'd:</l>
                     <l>'Tis now he juſtly will exact performance</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>your long Promis'd Mord,</hi> to extirpate</l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:151096:20"/>
                     <l>The Chriſtian Intereſt out of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, now is the Time, your Army's ſtaunch and ſtrong,</l>
                     <l>And your Pretences good to keep them up.</l>
                     <l>And ſince you have Power and Will, what can you doubt?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <l>But above all, remember <hi>Monumora,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>He muſt be lop'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <l>Great Sir, if Mercy can,</l>
                     <l>Without a hazard to the State or You,</l>
                     <l>Be ſhown,</l>
                     <l>'Twill be a God-like ſecond Conqueſt o're him,</l>
                     <l>To let him by your Royal Bounty Live.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <l>Rivals in Empires never can be ſpar'd</l>
                     <l>Without the general hazard of the Nation.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! Sir, 'tis moſt convenient he ſhould die.</l>
                     <l>'Slife I would not undergoe ſuch another Fright as he</l>
                     <l>Put me in for a Million of <hi>Monumora's.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(Aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <l>We ſhall debate theſe weighty Matters further,</l>
                     <l>But 'tis our Royal Pleaſure to depute</l>
                     <l>Our Truſty <hi>Barbaroſſa</hi> to go down,</l>
                     <l>And fix the Country in its due Obedience.</l>
                     <l>Examples may be made as you think fit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! my Diſcretion knows to limit thoſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE. II.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>The</hi> Queen<hi>'s</hi> Bed-chamber. <hi>The</hi> Scene <hi>draws, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers the</hi> Queen <hi>and</hi> Dadamore, <hi>riſing from the Bed.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, prithee leave this dull Formality;</l>
                     <l>I am <hi>Hautefelia</hi> ſtill to <hi>Dadamore;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Can'ſt thou yet doubt or wiſh for greater Proofs?</l>
                     <l>Come tell me, how do'ſt like my laſt Contrivance?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dad.</speaker>
                     <l>Fortune has been a Niggard to thy Merit,</l>
                     <l>And made but poor returns to thy Endeavours.</l>
                     <l>Tranſcendant Wit! and depth of Policy!</l>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:151096:21"/>
                     <l>VVhy pour <hi>Hungarian</hi> Politicians will be forc'd to borrow of you;</l>
                     <l>Thou art Invention in the Abſtract!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Let your Grave Philoſophers keep a pother about their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities and Quidities, one flight of a VVomans Fancy would ruin the niceſt of their Diſtinctions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dad.</speaker>
                     <p>And what's no mean Ornament to your Atchievments, to have Succeſs like a Lacquey, ſtill keeping pace with you; ſo that you no ſooner grow big with a Project, but ſhe like a Mid-wiſe, ſtands ready to deliver you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Let their Chriſtian <hi>Sanhedrims</hi> now pore upon their Fear and Jealouſies, I think I have ſitted them with <hi>a Bill of Excluſion.</hi> O! how my hopes do antedate the tedious Months. Well, this is a Revenge worthy my ſelf, to ſatisfie my Love, my Ambition, and my Intereſt at once: Why, it will make the <hi>Muſti,</hi> and whole Conclave bluſh to ſee themſelves ſo much out-done: And then my Lovely <hi>Dadamore,</hi> 'twill be no mean or trifling Pleaſure to thee, to have, perhaps, a long Succeſſive Race of Pagan Kings, ſprung from thy very Loins; beſide, the expectance of a vaſt Reward from our moſt Holy Prophet, for thy care thus to improve his People's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dad.</speaker>
                     <p>But, Madam, grant (for we'll ſuppoſe the worſt) that this ſhould fail,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>It is impoſſible, did not our Holy Virgin, the Great <hi>Loretto,</hi> promiſe me Succeſs; hear the Words of the <hi>Oracle:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <l>By thy Induſtrious Zeal and Prayers I'm won,</l>
                        <l>To grant and promiſe thou ſhalt have a Son;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Italian</hi> Strength, or <hi>Gallick</hi> Policy,</l>
                        <l>Shall help to enlarge thy great Poſterity.</l>
                        <l>'Tis order'd he muſt ſhare a double Fate;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A Peaſant Born, a Prince Regenerate.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dad.</speaker>
                     <p>VVhy, 'tis a ſort of Riddle.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! your Oracles always ſpeak in that manner, but the Key to explain it was ſent with this: I have the ſenſe of it at my Fingers ends. In ſhort, my Dear <hi>Dadamore,</hi> the Secret is this, that if the Envious Stars Conſpire to render our Embraces fruitleſs, we muſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151096:21"/>have recourſe to the other extream: Time preſſes hard, and we may be ſure to have the Curſe of our Prophet, if for want of an Heir, we ſhould let the Inheritance of Mother-Church fall to Strangers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Queen is going.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ded.</speaker>
                     <l>This is an admirable Fetch: VVell,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For Wit, Religion, Honeſty, let no Man</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hereafter vainiy think to vie with <hi>Woman.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Aſide. Exeunt</hi> Qu. Dad.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE III. Alba Regalis.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Remarquo, Pietro.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>VVell, <hi>Remarquo,</hi> who is the Chriſtians King now?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pietro.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha, ha, how do you make that out <hi>Remarquo?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>VVhy the Queen Governs the King, and <hi>Pietro</hi> Rules the Queen, ſo in effect <hi>Pietro</hi> is King.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>I don't like your Jeſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>I don't like your <hi>Earneſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou talkeſt as big as if thou hadſt another <hi>Monumora</hi> at thy back.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>If I have, <hi>you'll not ſtay to look him in the Face:</hi> I have one in ſtore yet, for your Confeſſor-ſhip. He may raiſe the Price of Hemp as much as <hi>Barbaroſſa,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, prithee be Civil <hi>Remarquo,</hi> and lets talk of the News. You were at <hi>Monumora</hi>'s Execution; how did he behave himſelf?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>As an Honeſt Man would do amongſt a Company of Knaves; what he thought fit to ſay, he knew would not be ſuffer'd; and what they would have him, he ſcorn'd; and there's and End of his Speech: Your Worſhip will make a longer perhaps, when your turn comes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>VVell, <hi>Remarquo,</hi> I pitty him; but the Cauſe, <hi>Remarquo,</hi> the Cauſe muſt go forward.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(<hi>Exit</hi> Pie.)</stage>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:151096:22"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>If the Cauſe (as he calls it) and his Worſhip had been Hang'd Twenty Years ago, I would have been at the trouble of Pitying him too: Pity quoth he? Poor <hi>Hungary</hi> will never be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py till he is ſo Pitied.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Rem.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE IV. Aceldama <hi>in the</hi> Weſt.</head>
                  <stage>[<hi>The Scene opens, and diſcovers</hi> Barbaroſſa <hi>ſitting in Judgment; on each ſide ſtands Officers with Axes, Halters, burning Irons, Racks, Whips,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>One ſide of the Stage is Crowded up with Priſoners, which by a Guard are ſurrounded: The Cryer makes Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of</hi> Silence, <hi>and then the Court proceeds to the</hi> Tryals: <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſo, Warranto, all the while are ſhuffling up and down to get Bribes of the Priſoners, and proffering the Sale of</hi> Pardons. <hi>After the Indictments againſt ſeveral Read, the</hi> Clerke <hi>bids the</hi> Cryer <hi>call the King's Evidence,</hi> Timoroſo, Trecheronto, Gripe, <hi>who appearing,</hi> Barbaroſſa <hi>begins.</hi>]</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Here you Mr. <hi>Timoroſa,</hi> you look like an Honeſt Man: Come, do you know theſe Men at the Bar? Look on them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, my Lord, I ſhould know them, but my Memory is bad, I have forgot them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Speak out Man, thou art afraid, Did'ſt not thou ſee thoſe Fellows here Arm'd, and Engaging like Sturdy Rebels in the Duke of <hi>Monumora</hi>'s Army, againſt our Soveraign Lord <hi>Cullida?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                     <p>O Lord, Sir, I was never in an Engagement my Self, but I ſaw thoſe Men all; and ſome of them with brown Bills, Scythes, and Hatchets.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſaw them among the Rebels?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, I dont know Rebels from other Folke.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>He frowns and ſtorms at him.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                     <p>But the Truth on't is, they have the very <hi>Looks</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(in a fearful tone.)</stage>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:151096:22"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou haſt the <hi>Look</hi> of a Hobby-Horſe. Set up the next there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Firſt Priſoner.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, perhaps he might ſee me with a Bill on my Shoulder; I was going to the Field about my buſineſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>You were going to the Field to Plow with your Bill: Yes, you went to Sow Rebellion, and you'll Reap Halters: This is your Chriſtian Religion, as you call it! Well, you'll not ſcruple to Die Martyrs for it. Come you Mr. <hi>Treacheronto,</hi> what can you tell us of theſe Men?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, I ſaw them every one hacking and hewing as if Old-<hi>Nick</hi> was in 'em.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Second Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Where was you when you ſaw us?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                     <p>Where was I? why, where I ſaw you, I warrant you: Nay, if you are for asking hard Queſtions, I'll fit you: My Lord, I ſaw that Man as fierce as a Dragon, I'll warrant he kill'd Fourteen or Fifteen himſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Here</hi> Diſpen. <hi>and</hi> War. <hi>come cloſe aſide the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, and whiſper them.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>What Murder and Rebellion! Come Sir, for your part you have ſaid enough.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Remarquo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diſ.</speaker>
                     <p>What Eſtate has this Gentleman, Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>to one of the Priſ.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Near Four Hundred <hi>per Annum.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>War.</speaker>
                     <p>A fair Eſtate, 'tis pitty it ſhould be all loſt to himſelf and Family.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, the Judge is my very good Friend, and I pity your Condition, I ſhall do my endeavours for you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>War.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, Sir, he carries a great ſtroak with him, and you know Life is ſweet, a Body would give ANY THING for ones Life.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Remarquo <hi>makes up and liſtens.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Wo is me, Sir, you ſhall Command all I have, ſo you will but ſave my Life.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Alack Sir, I don't <hi>value five hundred pounds,</hi> 'tis pure Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that I ſtir in it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>VVho in the Name of Goodneſs have we here?</p>
                     <stage>(Aſide.)</stage>
                     <p>O my Conſcience, the <hi>Muſti</hi>'s Blood-hounds, and <hi>Barbaroſſa</hi>'s
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151096:23"/>Purſe-Bearers, the two Law-Butchers that comes every Seſſions and Aſſize, and grope the Priſoners, as Graziers do their Cattle, to ſee if they be Fat, and well to paſs; then if there's hopes of a handſom Greaſing, they preſently give their Maſter the hint, who extends his Mercy, as Rooking Gameſters at firſt loſe their Money, only to draw you in for a deeper ſtake: But hold, I'll mark the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diſp.</speaker>
                     <p>But, Sir, the Truth on't is <hi>(ſpeaking to the Priſoner)</hi> my Lord's Servants will expect ſomething conſiderably.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, the Five Hundred Pounds ſhall be ready in two Hours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, you ſee Gentlemen, the Evidence is plain againſt you, what have you more to ſay? What do they ſay <hi>Diſpenſo?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>So there's the watch VVord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diſp.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, there is Mr. <hi>Wealthy</hi> and his Kinſ-man, wholly throw themſelves upon the King's Mercy, I believe they have been deluded.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, in my Conſcience, if the Devil had been in their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and you too to have dealt with him, he had been at a plaguy non-plus, if not out-done, in his own Maſter-piece of Cheating, Lying, Forgery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>VVell then, Gentlemen of the Jury, you have heard the full Evidence againſt the Priſoners, for the two black Crimes of Murther and Rebellion; the time will not admit of any long Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, we have other Buſineſs of the ſame Nature; only this I muſt tell you, they are plainly Guilty by the Law, and you cannot but bring them in ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fifth Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, I have not ſpoke one VVord for my ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! Sir, you need not ſay much, you have done more than you'll be able to anſwer while you live. VVhat ſay you, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of the King's Evidence, was not that Fellow amongſt them?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, my Lord, I muſt needs ſay, I know his Face very well. Yes, yes, he was one, a meer Rebel he. Now, I think on't he's a Creditor of mine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:151096:23"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, I deſire Juſtice, that Fellow owes me a hundred Pound, and thinks to come out of my Debt by falſly Accuſing me. Oh! Villain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>Do you hear, my Lord, would any but a Rebel A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the King's Evidence thus?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, Gentlemen of the Jury; I find they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing material to offer, ſo go out.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Jury.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Was there ever ſeen ſuch a Monſtrous Diſpenſer of Juſtice, that would rather throw away the Lives of ſo many poor Chriſtians without a hearing, than ſtay half an hour for his Dinner? Why, the Villain was certainly ſuckled with Blood; he does even thirſt after it: With what Ridicule and Buffoonry he us'd the poor Wretches! Not the half of 'em were ſuffer'd to ſpeak a word for their Lives.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Jury.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cryer.</speaker>
                     <p>Make way for the Jury there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>After the uſual Queſtions the Clark ſays.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
                     <p>How ſay you, is <hi>John Littlehope, &amp;c.</hi> Guilty of the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Treaſon for which they ſtand Indicted, or not Guilty?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jury.</speaker>
                     <p>Guilty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
                     <p>Goaler, look to your Priſoners.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, Gentlemen, you that are Priſoners there, and by the Law ſtand Convicted; as your Crimes have been of the blackeſt nature, ſo that you cannot in reaſon expect much Favour; ſo I ſhall proceed to give Sentence of Death according to Law.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>After which the Court breaks up, and <hi>Exeunt Omnes.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </div>
               <trailer>The End of the Third ACT.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:151096:24"/>
               <head>ACT IV.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>After a Proceſſion of</hi> Mahometan Prieſts <hi>and</hi> Choriſters, <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the</hi> Queen <hi>and</hi> Ladies, <hi>by way of Thansgiving for the</hi> Queens <hi>ſuppos'd being with Child; Enter</hi> Philanax, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marquo, Cellia <hi>the Queens Midwife.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>WIth Child, Man? 'Tis a Miracle!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>How! a Miracle! what, for a <hi>brisk Lady</hi> not yet thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be with Child? Why, prithee, there's not one in Fifty of the Sex but has a Colt's tooth in her Head at Threeſcore; tho' by the by (conſidering all things) I ſhould as ſoon have ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted my Grandmother as her Majeſty upon that ſcore.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(Aſide.)</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh dear, Sir <hi>Philanax,</hi> the Queen is <hi>full of Children,</hi> and what is more, I dare affirm, ſhe is <hi>going with a Prince,</hi> or I am very much miſtaken in the Stars.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, there's the thing? Theſe Pagans are the ſhrewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> they Calculate every thing to an hairs breadth; they have an <hi>Almanack</hi> fitted for every Meridian, and ſeldom fail in a Tittle of their Predictions.</p>
                     <stage>(Aſide)</stage>
                     <p>But, pray Madam, how long is ſhe gone?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                     <p>I am not acquainted with Particulars, but 'tis a bleſſing obtain'd from the <hi>Holy Virgin of Loretto.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhould have thought an Addreſs from her Majeſty, to ſome <hi>Holy broad-back'd Brother</hi> would have better befitted her Deſires and Circumſtances.</p>
                     <stage>(Aſide)</stage>
                     <p>But what Applications did the Virgin preſcribe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! ſhe ſent her a Smock of a Generative Faculty, I'll warrant ye we ſhall never want a Prince now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:151096:24"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, nay, now I remember, Madam, the Receipt was ſound out near an hundred years agone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, yes, it has lain dormant among the Pagan Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks ever ſince <hi>Hantefelia</hi> the Firſt, and now for the <hi>good</hi> of the Kingdom, and <hi>Advantage</hi> of <hi>Holy Mother Church,</hi> 'tis bruſh'd up anew; but this won't do.</p>
                     <stage>(Aſide)</stage>
                     <p>Well, Madam, Increaſe of the Royal Iſſue is a great Bleſſing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! we ſhall ſee glorious Times in <hi>Hungary, Remarquo,</hi> Theſe puling Chriſtians make ſuch a ſtrange pother about <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> and I know not what, that they ſpoil all the <hi>good Intentions</hi> of the King and Queen. Thoſe Patients can never expect to be well Cur'd, that won't follow the Advice of their Phyſicians.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, Madam, I muſt needs confeſs we are in a lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Condition; but by the way, we ſhould be as little behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her for <hi>her</hi> way of Cure, as I ſhould be to be knock'd o'th' head by the way of putting me out of pain, when yet there was pregnant hopes of my Recovery.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, Sir <hi>Philanax,</hi> the Queens Delivery will put an end to, and ſatisfie all our Fears and Jealouſies.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Cel.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                     <p>Spoke like an Oracle efaith!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, yes, the Queens Midwife, you muſt know, ſpeaks with abundance of <hi>fore-knowledge.</hi> Satisfie their Fears and Jealouſies, ſaid ſhe? Yes, her Majeſties <hi>Delivery</hi> (as they call it) will <hi>ſatisfie</hi> all <hi>Parties;</hi> the Pagans, becauſe they hope to bring their old Plot of a <hi>Sham Prince</hi> to perfection; and the Chriſtians, no doubt, will be ſatisfied of the Cheat. Well, I ſhall live, I hope, to ſee her Majeſty and this Kingdom <hi>fitted</hi> with a <hi>Delivery.</hi> I believe, indeed, her Majeſty has made as curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a ſearch, and taken as much bodily Pains for an Heir, as ever Chymiſt did for the Philoſopher's Stone: But, alas! a Body might as ſoon extract Gold out of a Flint, as hope for a Child from ſuch known deprav'd and ſickly Conſtitutions; I hear by <hi>Mazato,</hi> indeed, that the Count and her Majeſty have made many Experiments about it, but can't nick it; ſo now they
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151096:25"/>have reſolv'd to trump up the old Game, and play the Tune of her Majeſties <hi>Name ſake</hi> of <hi>Pious</hi> Memory, Well, I'll ſtick as cloſe to her as the Shadow to the Subſtance, he ſhall never make uſe of a Pot, but I, like a Phyſician, will be caſting her Water; I'll trace her to her very Bed, and obſerve every part of her; not the Promiſes of the King, nor the Threats of her ſelf, ſhall be able to delude or frighten me. No, I love my King as my Father, but would not make him my Idol, and Adore him; I honour him as my King, but will not with baſe Flattery blow him up to a <hi>Tyrant;</hi> I will obey him as a Diſpenſer <hi>of,</hi> but not with <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and above all, I'll prefer the ſafety and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of my Country in general, before the private Luſts, and unlawful wicked Deſigns of any Prince in Chriſtendom. And this, Sir <hi>Philanax,</hi> is or ought to be the firm Reſolution of every honeſt <hi>Hungarian.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
                     <p>And may the Plague of Pagan Tyranny light on him that wants it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Phil. Rem.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SCENE. II.</hi> The Palace of St. <hi>Jacques.</hi> The Queens <hi>Bed-Chamber.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Queen, Mazato, Sycophante, Midwife, Nurſe, <hi>&amp;c. at one door:</hi> Remarquo <hi>privately ſlips in at another, and huſhes himſelf up at a corner of the Hangings.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mid.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Majeſty will conſider, I preſume, that this being a Buſineſs of vaſt moment, it is to be managed with all the nici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty imaginable, the leaſt ſlip here, like the taking out the pin of a Watch, ſets the whole Work out of Order; and, what is amiſs here, is not like to be ever recovered.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Q.</speaker>
                     <p>I know all this, <hi>Cellia,</hi> and my own ſtrong Inclination, as well as former <hi>real</hi> Experince, ſhould, I fancy, put me out of all fear of failing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, you cannot be too perfect, you'll have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Eyes &amp; Ears about you; therefore my humble Advice is, That your Majeſty would not think it a trouble to practite it well before it comes to the Teſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:151096:25"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Q.</speaker>
                     <p>Let's ſee then <hi>Cellia,</hi> what muſt we do?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Here the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife opens a Bag and pulls out her Implements ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the better Delivery of Women of Quality.</stage>
                  <stage>Remarquo <hi>Peeps.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>So, ſo, the Play is <hi>compos'd</hi> and <hi>diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted,</hi> and now they are come to rehearſe their Parts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syc.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh dear <hi>Cellia,</hi> we ſhall have no uſe of them, 'twill be too publick for us, it muſt be all done in Bed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, I'll warrant you, with the Curtains cloſe drawn, and none but your Worſhips to fumble about her Queenſhip, and then if we ſail of a <hi>Sturdy Boy,</hi> let <hi>Old-Nick</hi> fail you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>That's the up ſhot of all, but there are <hi>praeliminaries</hi> to be conſidered.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cell.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, in the firſt place Your Majeſty will remember eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Morning you are to be taken with a ſmall fit of <hi>Hawking</hi> and <hi>Reaching,</hi> and now and then a <hi>Long-ſpit</hi> or two.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Syc.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh Madam, I remember a <hi>Qualm</hi> on the <hi>Stomach</hi> now and then is a very deluding thing (with the Men eſpecially) and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for a certain ſign of a <hi>growing Belly.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mid.</speaker>
                     <p>I remember how I <hi>bubbled</hi> a young Spark ſo once, who was fond of the <hi>conceit</hi> of having got me <hi>with Child,</hi> and when I had hook'd in ſome <hi>Preſents</hi> of conſiderable <hi>value,</hi> I feign'd a <hi>Miſcarriage,</hi> which coſt him a <hi>few Tears,</hi> and me a <hi>ſound Laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and there was an End of my <hi>Qualms;</hi> yes, yes, <hi>Qualms</hi> will go a great way.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Now if her Majeſty wanted a ſtock of <hi>Hypocriſie, &amp;c.</hi> She is got into good Company, and might be eaſily furniſhed: Oh the <hi>unſearchable Impudence</hi> of ſome Women!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mid.</speaker>
                     <p>In the next place, when your Majeſty would admit of much Company, you muſt yield to a <hi>Minutes Torture</hi> of being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>ſtrait Lac'd,</hi> which will be apt for the preſent to make you ready to <hi>Faint,</hi> which will add much to the Credit of your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>with Child,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maz.</speaker>
                     <p>That's a piece of Skill I was unacquainted with till now, Madam <hi>Cellia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:151096:26"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mid.</speaker>
                     <p>From the quickning of the Child, proceeds Motion in the <hi>Womb,</hi> which diſturbing ſome <hi>Fibres</hi> that go up to the <hi>Heart,</hi> cauſeth <hi>Palpitations, &amp;c.</hi> and thence proceed <hi>Swooning, Faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Short-breathings, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ren.</speaker>
                     <p>On my <hi>Conſcience,</hi> I ſhall have a ſweet Lecture of <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Philoſophy,</hi> ſhe'll run over <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Problems preſently.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Q.</speaker>
                     <p>If <hi>Swoonings</hi> and <hi>Faintings</hi> be a Rule you preſcirbe, I can eaſily perform it; but <hi>Mazato,</hi> and all of you, remember to looſen me preſently, or I may be ſick indeed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> 
                     <hi>Note, That this was the conſtant Remedy for all the late Queen of</hi> Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary<hi>'s Swooning Fits, during her pretened Bigneſs.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mid.</speaker>
                     <p>Binding in the back, like one that is overburthen'd, is ſo natural a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of a <hi>Great Belly,</hi> that Your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty will not, I believe, need Inſtructions concerning it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, now from a Mothodical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of theſe <hi>weighty Inſtructions,</hi> a body might make a ſhift to pick up a <hi>Moderate Maintenance;</hi> why, I ſhall be a perfect <hi>Midwife;</hi> there's many a Man has ſet up his Trade, that has not Learn'd half ſo much on't, as I have of this.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(Aſide.)</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mid.</speaker>
                     <p>Now Madam, we muſt be bold with your Majeſties <hi>Belly,</hi> for that is, as it were, the <hi>Primum Mobile</hi> of our <hi>Intrigue,</hi> and muſt be ordered with abundance of Nicety.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(The Midwife and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies come up cloſe to the Queen, and feel and grope about the Queens Belly, and then lift up her Petticoats.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Udsbud, what are they going to do now?
<stage>(Remarquo <hi>peeps, he ſhrugs and ſcratches.</hi>
                        </stage> Oh lau! <hi>Treaſon, Treaſon!</hi> 'Dsfleſh, if I ſhould be caught here now, I ſhould be hang'd as round as a hoop, for committing <hi>Treaſon</hi> againſt her Majeſties <hi>Belly;</hi> well, I don't care, I'll carry a good Conſcience with me, I will not ſee. <stage>(Aſide.)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(He holds his hands before his Face, and peeps thro' his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mid.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Majeſty muſt have it height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by degrees, it muſt carry a Simimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of a <hi>Natural Swelling.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:151096:26"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>This is an odd way of getting a Son, an Heir, though:<stage>(Here they place a ſmall Cuſhion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her Cloaths.</stage> What, a few Rags pinn'd together, muſt perſonate the Prince, and we ſhall have ſome neighbouring Monarchs, ſent to, and Solicited to ſtand <hi>God-Fathers</hi> to a <hi>Piſs-burnt Cuſhion:</hi> Well, they may get what <hi>Infant</hi> they pleaſe to compleat the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy;</hi> but I'll engage he ſhall ſtand to his <hi>Pedigree,</hi> and never be any thing in <hi>Hungary,</hi> but King of his Mothers <hi>Clowts.</hi>
                        <stage>(Aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>All theſe are but trifles, <hi>Sycophant,</hi> my own Ingenuity will undertake theſe; but the very <hi>Critical</hi> Minute, <hi>Celia,</hi> that's the grand Queſtion, theſe <hi>Plaguy Chriſtians</hi> are ſo miſtruſtful, they'll not take ones word for any thing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis very hard, conſidering her Majeſty deals ſo <hi>Iuſtly</hi> by them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(Aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mid.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, young Pupils muſt of neceſſity ſubmit to the Experince and Doctrine of their Elders; this is not the firſt buſineſs of this nature that I have manag'd, and with your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Patience, I'll draw you a <hi>Scheme</hi> of all we are to do, in a moment.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee <hi>Celia,</hi> I have Inclination and knowledge, but my <hi>Modeſty will be at a ſtand.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O Lau! O Lau!</hi> Modeſty, ſaid ſhe? She has been at the Court of <hi>Hungary</hi> theſe ten years, where <hi>Whoring, Lying, &amp;c.</hi> have been improv'd at the rate of <hi>Fifty per Cent,</hi> and now ſhe pretends to boggle at a little. <hi>Diſſembling:</hi> Yes, yes, I have heard Count <hi>Dadamore</hi> and her Queenſhip, Con over <hi>Lectures of Modeſty,</hi> till they ſweat again.</p>
                     <stage>(Aſide.)</stage>
                     <p>Oh! She's a very Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot in <hi>Modeſty,</hi> when ſhe lights of an <hi>induſtrious Tutor.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(Aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>However, <hi>Cellia</hi> conſidering the neceſſity, I'll over-run all difficulties.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Her Highneſs is very poſitive; She and her <hi>Jehuſites</hi> have made it their buſineſs to wrangle us out of our Senſes, if they could; and the King has not left us the diſpoſal even of one <hi>Thought, <hi>for he tells us we are to give an implicite Obedience without</hi> Reſerve,</hi> ſo that if all other means fail, for ought we know, we may have the <hi>Daughter of an Elephant</hi> trump't up
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151096:27"/>with a Declaration of <hi>Hic est filius meus,</hi> and who dare diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute or gain ſay it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(Aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                     <p>Well then, Madam, in the firſt place, ſuppoſe your ſelf handſomely laid in Bed, between <hi>nine and ten</hi> in the Morning, and no Company but your own Truſty Friends, the Chriſtians ſafe at their Devotion <hi>(the Prelates eſpecially must be abſent.)</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! Foh, if I had a mind to ſave Charges, I'd take no other Phyſick than the ſight of a <hi>Chriſtian Prelate.</hi> Oh! what a ſtrange working it has caus'd in my Stomach, the very name of them is a Vomit.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(She ſpits.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                     <p>Nor indeed muſt any other of them come within ſight of you, they'll make ſuch a noiſe with impertinent Queſtions, as may ſpoil your Milk, as you know Thunder does Ale.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>There's ſome hopes of this, Lady <hi>Midwife;</hi> her Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry I ſee is ſhort, and ſhe may be out in her Leſſon, ſhe's afraid of ſpoiling her Milk, when they had agreed before, ſhe could have none; but 'tis the nature of ſome people <hi>to tell a lie ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that at last they perſwade themſelves 'tis true.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(Aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Alack! You may be ſure <hi>Cullidada</hi> will take care to keep them at the farther part of the Room, where you know out of common complaiſance, they muſt harangue him upon his <hi>Vnexpected</hi> Happineſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Of having a Child beyond all poſſibility.</hi> 
                        <stage>(Aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>You are in the right on't, Madam; then for two or three faint Cries (ſuch as I gave when I made my Husband believe he was tearing my Maidenhead to pieces, and a little buſtling about the Cloaths, and out comes the <hi>Young Perkin,</hi> as like the Father as if he were <hi>ſpit out</hi> of his Mouth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>But as to the cleanly conveying him in; <hi>we forgot that, Celia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                     <p>That I'll ſhew you in a moment.</p>
                     <stage>(She goes to one corner of the Stage, and brings a large warming Pan lin'd with Velvet.</stage>
                     <p>Now Madam, juſt before the critical minute, you call of courſe to have the bed warm'd, then in comes <hi>me, Madam Midwife,</hi>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:151096:27"/>with this Warming-pan, mark you me, with young <hi>Perkin</hi> as ſung in it as a <hi>drowned Toaſt</hi> in the bottom of a Tankard; then while you are undreſſing and ready to pop in, whip, I ſtrait diſembogue and leave your Majeſty the hopeful Mother of a luſty Son and Heir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>So, ſo, this is an excellent way to hinder collateral deſcents: Why, who would be ſo fooliſh to pine for an Heir, when every Midwife in Town can ſo eaſily ſupply them?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, this <hi>Cellia</hi> is an Artiſt, Ladies: Well, thou haſt ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me to a miracle: I long for the good hour. Oh, I have it now at my fingers ends.</p>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pagans rejoyce, our Mufti do's agree,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This Year ſhould be to us a Jubilee,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>[Exit Qu. cum ſuis,</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>manet Rem.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <l>Pagans beware, for we ſhall take occaſion,</l>
                     <l>To tax your works of <hi>Supererogation.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>We ſcorn your Preſidents, and ne're can own</l>
                     <l>Such ſpurious Sons, as fill our <hi>Neighbouring Throne;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Spight of your frauds we ſhall be ſhortly free</l>
                     <l>From Tyrant Kings, and <hi>Pagan Slavery.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Exit Rem.</stage>
               </div>
               <trailer>Finis Act. 4ti.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>ACT. V.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene I.</head>
                  <stage>The Scene opens and diſcovers <hi>Cullidada</hi> alone, leaning penſively on a Table, and endeavouring to raiſe himſelf; he is in a moment environed with a great Company of Ghoſts, which riſe out of the Ground, and point ſeverally at him, ſhaking their Heads at one another. The firſt is that of the Sieur <hi>Godferus,</hi> ſometime one of the Tribunes of the People of <hi>Hungary,</hi> his Head ſeems to dangle from one ſide to the other, as if his Neck were broken, and has his own Sword ſticking through him as he nods to the oppoſite Ghoſt, which is that of <hi>Columona,</hi> who holds; out to the King the end of a Rope, which is faſtened about his Neck. The next is Monſieur <hi>Stephano de la Colledge,</hi> with a Halter about his Neck. The next is the Count <hi>de Eſſeycke,</hi> who points to his Throat, which is cut ſo deep, that his Head ſeems ready to fall off. The next are the Lord <hi>Roſſellio,</hi> and the Sieur <hi>le Sydeny,</hi> who have two Golden Rings about their Necks, by which their Heads ſeem to be
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151096:28"/>faſtened to their Bodies. The next is the Ghoſt of the Sieur <hi>del Aramſtrough,</hi> with an Halter about his Neck, and an Ax in his hand. The next is the Burgomaſter <hi>Coroniſe,</hi> with an Halter in his hand. In the midſt of all is the Ghoſt of the Prince <hi>Philodemy,</hi> Duke of <hi>Monumora,</hi> who has alſo a Golden Ring round his Neck, <hi>and a Crown ſeems to hang over him</hi> ſome ſmall diſtance from his Head. After two or three horrid Flaſhes of Lightning and Claps of Thunder, the Ghoſt of <hi>Godferus</hi> ſpeaks:</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Ghoſt of</hi> Godf.</speaker>
                     <l>SEE, <hi>Cruel Prince,</hi> thy Trade of Cruelty,</l>
                     <l>Which was firſt practis'd and begun on me:</l>
                     <stage>The Ghoſt points round to the reſt.</stage>
                     <l>Love to my Country, and the Kingdoms Peace,</l>
                     <l>(Which ſure deſerves reward, at leaſt ſhould pleaſe,)</l>
                     <l>Made me, Oh! Strange Ingratitude! incur</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thy Cruel Rage</hi>—</l>
                     <l>'Tis true, with zealous Induſtry I ran</l>
                     <l>And trac'd the bloody Steps of thy <hi>Mysterious Babylon:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>There was my Crime; And here my Puniſhment:</l>
                     <l>Nor is thine far behind. Repent, Repent;</l>
                     <stage>[Pointing to his Neck.</stage>
                     <l>Thy Fate's determin'd, and the Time draws on:</l>
                     <l>Thy Crown (by <hi>Fratricide</hi> obtain'd) is gone;</l>
                     <l>Thy Life's inglorious, troubleſome and ſhort,</l>
                     <l>To Friends a Burden, to thy Foes a Sport.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Ghoſt of</hi> Col.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah! my <hi>ungrateful</hi> Maſter, are you here?</l>
                     <l>Your cheated Secretary does appear,</l>
                     <l>Partly to chide your black Ingratitude,</l>
                     <l>That could ſo eaſily betray my Blood;</l>
                     <l>But chiefly to inform you, you miſtake,</l>
                     <l>If for a <hi>Saint</hi> you <hi>Columena</hi> take.</l>
                     <l>Believe me, Sir, (and Spirits ſeldom lie)</l>
                     <l>You are your ſelf as much a <hi>Saint</hi> as I.</l>
                     <l>Ah, much more likely 'tis, you may be one,</l>
                     <l>Since Providence permits your Glaſs to run,</l>
                     <l>And gives you time to think, and mend your Errors;</l>
                     <l>(For after Death you cannot plead <hi>Demurrers.</hi>)</l>
                     <l>Ah! Think in time then, and repent your Evil,</l>
                     <l>Or elſe by <hi>Mahomet,</hi> you'll be a Devil.</l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:151096:28"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oh! Roguey Prieſts!</hi> How often they repeatrd;</l>
                     <l>If I'd conceal, how well I ſhould be treated?</l>
                     <l>If you'll believe them, <hi>you'll like me be cheated.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Ghoſt of</hi> Step. Col.</speaker>
                     <l>By perjur'd Tongues, ſuborn'd and brib'd by thee,</l>
                     <l>I fell the Victim of thy Cruelty,</l>
                     <l>No Age, nor Sex, nor Quality was free</l>
                     <l>From the baſe Inſults of thy Tyranny.</l>
                     <l>Through all Degrees of Wickedneſs thou'ſt gone,</l>
                     <l>Through all the murth'ring Arts of curſed <hi>Babylon:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor Prince, nor Peaſant, Lords nor Commons ſtood</l>
                     <l>Free from thy cruel Thirſt of ſhedding Blood.</l>
                     <l>Thy Friends ſcarce pity thee, thy Foes deſpiſe;</l>
                     <l>And Heaven, who ſees the Juſtice of our Cries,</l>
                     <l>Has curſt thee—</l>
                     <l>Thy Fate's determin'd in the Eternal Roll,</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt <hi>with Speed</hi> and <hi>Ignominy fall:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>All that thy cruel Subtilty has done,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Shall in the compaſs of one ſhort liv'd Sun,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Be loſt, unravell'd, ſpurn'd and trod upon.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Ghoſt of</hi> Eſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Unhappy Prince! by what blind Fury led,</l>
                     <l>Doſt thou delight theſe Paths of Blood to tread?</l>
                     <l>Does thy inſatiate <hi>Moloch</hi> ſtill require</l>
                     <l>More of thy Sons to paſs the fatal Fire?</l>
                     <l>Does thy ſtrange Principles and Zeal o'rethrow</l>
                     <l>All ties of Blood, of Vertue, and of Law?</l>
                     <l>Will not the Father, King, nor Friend controul</l>
                     <l>The wild Exceſſes of thy boundleſs Soul?</l>
                     <l>Ah! Prince look back, ſee what a Multitude</l>
                     <stage>[The King looks back affrighted.</stage>
                     <l>Of pale-fac'd threatning Ghoſts about thee croud,</l>
                     <l>All earneſt Suppliants at th' Heavenly Throne</l>
                     <l>For Vengeance on thy Guilty Head alone;</l>
                     <l>And they've obtain'd; thy <hi>Fate</hi> is written <hi>there,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>ſoon</hi> thoul't find it executed <hi>here.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Ghoſt of</hi> Roſſel.</speaker>
                     <l>Pity, a Stranger to thy Savage Soul,</l>
                     <l>Does yet my juſt Reſentments ſo controul,</l>
                     <l>That at the Throne of Grace I am become</l>
                     <l>A Suppliant to reverſe thy fearful Doom.</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:151096:29"/>
                     <l>But oh! thy unrelenting Soul denies</l>
                     <l>Even Pity to thy ſelf, nay, and defies,</l>
                     <l>Like hardned Rebels, all juſt Terms of Peace;</l>
                     <l>Thou wouldſt not bid one Tear for thy Eternal Eaſe.</l>
                     <l>Hear therefore what the Fates have now ordain'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thy Crown is loſt, thy Fame for ever ſtain'd:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A Prince for <hi>God-like Qualities renown'd</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shall raiſe the <hi>Groveling Kingdom</hi> from the Ground</l>
                     <l>And ſtop the Torrent of its bleeding Wounds,</l>
                     <l>In baſe Diſguiſe thou ſhalt obſcurely fly</l>
                     <l>Be made the ſport of every common Eye,</l>
                     <l>And dwindle a ſhort tedious Life in Miſery.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>As ſoon as the Ghoſt of Lord</hi> Roſſelio <hi>has done ſpeaking, all the reſt of the Ghoſts clap their hands aloud, and pointing and laughing at</hi> Cullydada, <hi>they dance round him: Only the Ghoſt of</hi> Monumora <hi>ſeems penſive, and ſhakes his head in a lamenting manner, which the King takes much notice of; and in a trembling manner ventures to come a little towards him, and ſpeaks:</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>King.</speaker>
                     <l>By that Divine and Glorious Form, I gueſs</l>
                     <l>If Ghoſts may carry Names, thou art <hi>Monumora,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Valiant Son of my moſt Royal Brother.</l>
                     <stage>[The Ghoſt nods in token of aſſent.</stage>
                     <l>Thou ſeem'ſt to carry on that ſolid Brow</l>
                     <l>More of calm Sorrow than of juſt Revenge:</l>
                     <l>Good Heavens! He ſeems to weep! his ſhaking Head</l>
                     <l>Seems to lament the Miſery that waits me.</l>
                     <l>Speak, Holy Shade, canſt thou forgive the Wrongs</l>
                     <l>Which cruel Policy of State, and ſordid Fear,</l>
                     <l>Prompted by bloody Importunites,</l>
                     <l>Of an imperious Wife, and Crafty Prieſt,</l>
                     <l>Made me commit?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ghoſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Repent, and I forgive.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <stage>[Sighs and groans heavily]</stage>
                     <l>This is the firſt time my hardned Heart</l>
                     <l>E're melted with Remorſe: Oh! the ſharp Sting</l>
                     <l>Of a Relenting Guilty Conſcience!</l>
                     <l>Dear Shade, accept my juſt unfeigned Sorrow</l>
                     <l>(The only Recompenſe I now can make)</l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:151096:29"/>
                     <l>Thy undeſerved goodneſs has o'recome me,</l>
                     <l>And I am now all over Penitence:</l>
                     <l>Oh! that I could reverſe the Book of Fate,</l>
                     <l>And re-inſtate thee on the Earth again;</l>
                     <l>Methinks 'twould eaſe me of a <hi>Load</hi> of Sin,</l>
                     <l>If to my troubled Conſcience I could plead</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Not Guilty</hi> of the Death of <hi>Monumora</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ghoſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Repent, and I forgive.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[He is going.]</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay, Sacred Shade, and ſince thy Goodneſs can</l>
                     <l>With ſo much eaſe forgive; let me prevail</l>
                     <l>From thy Divine Intelligence, to learn</l>
                     <l>The utmoſt of that Fate that threatens me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>The Ghoſt is juſt going to ſpeak, and the Cock Crows, at which they ſtart, and ſhaking their Heads at</hi> Cullydada, <hi>they Vaniſh.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Enter Meſſenger.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, I was hither from the <hi>Low-Lands</hi> ſent</l>
                     <l>With Letters to your Sacred Majeſty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[He gives the Letters, and the K. Reads, he ſtarts and ſtamps.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <l>Five Hundred Sail! and Forty Thouſand Men!</l>
                     <l>And ready juſt to Sail: Did you ſee any?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis too true, my Liege, 'twas whiſper'd there,</l>
                     <l>They'd Sayl the Morning Tyde.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <l>And is it certain</l>
                     <l>That they deſign to Invade our Kingdom here?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>At firſt the Rumours were ſo various,</l>
                     <l>We could not fix on any Certainty;</l>
                     <l>But 'tis no longer now a Secret made,</l>
                     <l>That they deſign their Courſe for <hi>Hungary.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Exit Meſſ.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>K.</speaker>
                     <stage>[muſes]</stage>
                     <l>This unexpected Storm does more confound me,</l>
                     <l>Than all the threatning Dangers of my Life.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Five Hundred Sail of Ships!</hi> 'tis wonderful,</l>
                     <l>Mann'd, Victual'd, Fix'd, and ready to Hoiſe Sayl,</l>
                     <l>And all with ſuch profound ſtrange Privacy!</l>
                     <l>It ſeems to carry fatal Omens with it,</l>
                     <l>Since Providence already ſeems to fide with them:</l>
                     <l>Sure my Prophetick Ghoſts could never mean</l>
                     <l>To ſpur my eager Fate ſo quickly on:</l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:151096:30"/>
                     <l>And I deſign'd, if time had been allow'd,</l>
                     <l>T' have taken all effectual humane means</l>
                     <l>To baffle their pretended Fate—</l>
                     <l>If Shoals of Gallick Friends and bold <hi>Hiberians</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Could have perform'd what I ſo long deſign'd,</l>
                     <l>They ſhould have ſwarm'd in all their Chriſtian Hives,</l>
                     <l>And turn'd their murmuring Hoſts a grazing:</l>
                     <l>But ſtill I'll not deſpair.</l>
                     <l>Induſtrious Wiſdom often does prevent</l>
                     <l>What lazy Folly thinks inevitable:</l>
                     <l>Big ſwelling Clouds are by the Winds blown o're,</l>
                     <l>And threatning ſtorms may dwindle into Showres.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Exit</hi> King.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>ACT. V. <hi>Scene II.</hi> The Moſque at the Palace of St. <hi>Jacques.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>The Scene draws and diſcovers</hi> Barbaroſſa, Pietro, <hi>and ſeveral Pagan Prieſts and Jebuſites in Conſultation.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Remarquo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>This News has ſtruck 'em all dumb; you can ſee nothing at Court but a Company of moving Statues; the Chriſtians whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper indeed, but the Pagans ſhake their Heads, as Phyſitians do when they give a Man over; and the King runs to and fro as if he were purſu'd by a Spirit or Goblin. I wonder where the <hi>good natur'd Pietro,</hi> and the <hi>Generons Barbaroſſa</hi> are, I have not ſeen them at <hi>Alba Regalis</hi> all this Evening; I'll warrant you, one is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting the good of the Chriſtians Souls, as the other did of their Bodies in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> and are as <hi>calm in their Conſciences</hi> as the meek ſuffering Martyrs; and as little diſturb'd at the News, as a Hare at the firſt opening of the Kennel. Well, I'll go in and viſit ſome of their Active Brethren, who at this time now are wonderful buſie in forging falſe Reports, to ſcatter amongſt the People. Had who have we yonder? Oh there's</p>
                     <stage>[He is going forward.]</stage>
                     <p>the Jebuſites private Cabal; now they are preparing buſineſs to be offer'd in Council; a Company of true <hi>State-Tinkers,</hi> who under the pretence of mending one Fault, make twenty. Well, I muſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151096:30"/>be <hi>incognito;</hi> I'll ſtand up here and liſten, I may edifie upon it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>We have no time, Gentlemen, to make long Speeches: let us each offer our Sentiments, and from thence we'll pick out mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the fitteſt Propoſals to be made to <hi>Cullydada.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 <hi>Jeb.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>What are the Heads of the Prince <hi>Lyſander</hi>'s Declaration?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>I am afraid the Reverend <hi>Pietro</hi>'s and mine are <hi>two of them.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, And I hope he'll have better hold of them, that in his Declaration. <stage>[aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Jeb.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Does our Danger proceed from the Perſon of the Prince?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! He's the <hi>Primum Mobile</hi> of the Faction.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Jeb.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Why then can we want a Zealous Brother, that will ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to give him a gentle touch under the <hi>Fifth Rib?</hi> 'Tis the way of the Pagans, and according to the Inſtructions of <hi>Mother-Church.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>I confeſs 'tis <hi>lawful,</hi> but not at this time <hi>ſeaſonable;</hi> we muſt uſe Lenitives yet a while; we may have a time yet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, yes; I may ſee them all take their turns in good time. <stage>[aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>The Plaguy Chriſtian Nobles adviſe the King forthwith to call the <hi>Sanhedrim.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[They all ſtart at the Word.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! how they wince at the very name of it?<stage>[aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Vdsbud, a Sanhedrim!</hi> Why, the very thought of one's as dreadful as the ſight of a Death's Head, and there's a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento mori</hi> to us included in the very Words.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>Alack, my Breath ſmells of <hi>Hemp</hi> ever ſince you mention'd it: Why, prithee what was our buſineſs here for theſe many long years, but to <hi>ſtave</hi> off Sanhedrims, unleſs now and then to let them come together for matter of Form, and to fill the Kings Coffers, <hi>which we always made ſure to employ againſt themſelves.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, I had as lief take a Lion by the Paw, as look a <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> in the Face, they have ſuch a plaguy way of making a Man dancing the <hi>Somerſet</hi> before 'em, and turning him inſide out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: I ſhould not be my ſelf again while I liv'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:151096:31"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, o'my Conſcience, there muſt be a great <hi>dearth of Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> here, if you liv'd long after. <stage>aſide</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jeb.</speaker>
                     <p>But how do the People behave themſelves?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, there's the ſting. <stage>aſide</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>Why to be plain, As Malefactors at the Gallows, when they. ſee a <hi>Reprieve</hi> come, an unuſual blithneſs in the face of the better ſortſt and an inſulting boldneſs in the <hi>Rabble:</hi> I walkt the Streets laſt Night in Diſguiſe, on purpoſe to hear their Sentiments, where you ſhould ſee at every other Door private Caballers and publick Muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neers: At one place they ſtop'd me, and made me Drink Confuſion to <hi>Pietro,</hi> and his Holy Colleague the <hi>Chancellor:</hi> at another I ſaw a company of Boys were buſie in twiſting of <hi>Wattles</hi> I ask'd what they were for? They preſently return'd, to hang the <hi>Iebuſites</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and make a preſent of them to the <hi>Prince Liſander:</hi> Now this is our Diſtemper, Brother <hi>Barbaroſſa,</hi> what do you preſcribe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, I am at a ſtand; I have a plaguy Crick in my Neck of a ſuddain, and that's very ominous. Oh, that I had but two or three <hi>State Days</hi> in the Weſt again! Oh, 'twould be an infallible remedy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>R.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, your Worſhip need not doubt of making one Holy-day before you dye yet. <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Meſſenger.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord the King ſends for you both with all ſpeed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>What's the News prithee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>The Prince <hi>Lyſander</hi> is landed in the Weſt with a formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Army, and the <hi>Country</hi> pour in like Hail to him; ſome of the King's Troops have already entirely joyn'd him, and all the people declare unanimouſly for him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>B.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Oh poor Chancellor!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>P.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ah-poor Pietro!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>They run off, clapping and wringing their Hands.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:151096:31"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Scene III.</hi> Alba Regalis.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Queen tearing her Hair, and wringing her Hands, with <hi>Dada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi> the Nurſe with the pretended Prince; and <hi>Mazato, Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phante,</hi> and <hi>Remarquo</hi> at a diſtance.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh Villains! Rebels! Traytors! thus to betray their King and me. Are theſe their Chriſtian Principles? Foh!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>ſhe ſpits.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, there's the buſineſs: theſe ill-natur'd Chriſtians. Out upon 'em, that two or three Millions of Souls ſhould ſo una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly conſpire to ſave their <hi>ancient dear bought Laws</hi> from being ſubverted, their Religion from being violated, and their <hi>Throats from being Cut,</hi> when her Majeſty had ſuch a <hi>longing deſire</hi> for it. Indeed it was ill manners.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, if <hi>Barbaroſſa</hi> and the General had followed <hi>Pietro</hi>'s advice and mine, they ſhould not have left either Hive or Bee in that curſed <hi>Weſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, but the Soldiers are wiſer now; for to ſave ſhedding of Blood, they are all gone over to one ſide. <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dad.</speaker>
                     <p>Dear <hi>Hautefelia,</hi> do not ſo immoderately grieve, but think thy loving <hi>Dadamore</hi> ſhall ſtill ſupply all that envious For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune can take from thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Dear <hi>Dadamore,</hi> I muſt confeſs thou art the prop and ſtay of all my hopes; but—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Meſſenger.</stage>
                  <p>Speak; What's the News? make no preamble, be plain and ſhort.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>The King ſends word his Army is revolted; his very <hi>Friends, Relations,</hi> all are gone, and he's returning with all ſpeed for fear of being ſurprized by the Enemy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! <hi>Tortures, Plagues and Curſes</hi> ſeize them: Come, come my Friends, for you muſt ſhare my Fate.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Alack, if I ſhould loſe my <hi>Tommy</hi> now in this hurly burly!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>aſide: ſhe howles.</stage>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:151096:32"/>
                  <stage>Manet Remarq. Solus.</stage>
                  <stage>Exit Qu. cum ſuis</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rem.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh the hard Hearts of People grown in Sin!</l>
                     <l>She's ſenſible of the Plague that follows her,</l>
                     <l>But thinks not of the cauſe: her Coward Soul</l>
                     <l>(Eſſential to the wicked) now can pine and howl</l>
                     <l>At the apprehenſion of due puniſhment;</l>
                     <l>But with unimitable boldneſs ſhe</l>
                     <l>Could run through all the dreadful Catalogue</l>
                     <l>Of hainous Sins, without a doubt or ſcruple.</l>
                     <l>Nay ſhe does yet even refuſe to own,</l>
                     <l>Or to repent her Crimes againſt the Nation.</l>
                     <l>Her Crown, her State, her Grandeur, are the things</l>
                     <l>That cauſe her Tears and Curſes; but better far</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Some watry drops from her ſhould ſingly go,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Than Streams of Blood ſhou'd from the Nations flow.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Rem.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter King,</hi> Pietro, Barbaroſſa, Philanax, <hi>Meſſenger.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>King.</speaker>
                     <p>Does he deſign ſo ſuddenly to come?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Some of his Troops will quarter here to night.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>King</speaker>
                     <stage>pawſes a while.</stage>
                     <p>I'le anſwer all by a Meſſenger of mine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Meſſ.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>King.</speaker>
                     <p>Well my Friends, you ſee how Fate and Time preſs me? I have told you my deſigns, and this Night reſolve to put them in execution: the Queen and Child are ſafe gone off; and <hi>Pietro</hi> ſhe has left her Casket of Jewels to your care and charge.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le be her faithful Carrier: humh! the <hi>Iewels</hi> to my <hi>charge!</hi> Nay, there's a little comfort then; I find I ſhall not go empty handed. Yes, yes, I ſhall take care of them. <stage>aſide</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>King.</speaker>
                     <p>It begins to grow late, we muſt ſeparate: Well my good Friends, farewel; we may meet again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. K. Bar. Pie.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Rabble; with Links and Staves, ſhouting and hollowing.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Come, come, away Boys, away; the King has ſlip'd away, but we'll claw his Pagans off.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Ay, ay, let's pull down their Houſes; they have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151096:32"/>of <hi>Croſſes and Beads</hi> in them: Oh I hate Croſſes; there's none but Heathens love Croſſes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Ay let's pull down Count—<hi>what de call'ems houſe;</hi> Oh he's a <hi>deviliſh Pagan,</hi> there's abundance of Gold and Money there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Nay, then it deſerves to be pull'd down: I'le warrant you they worſhip it there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>5 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Ay, and there's Goodman <hi>Fangum,</hi> he's a Plaguy Fellow; Iowe him for two Suits of Cloaths indeed, but he rayl'd ſo ſadly againſt <hi>Prince Lyſander,</hi> that I have no mind to pay him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>6 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Come, come, we will lay down our Lives for the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, and ſo 'tis unreaſonable theſe <hi>Pagans</hi> ſhould have ſuch a deal of Money; come, away Boys, away.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Pietro <hi>diſguis'd, like a Tinker with a Budget at his Back.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>So honeſt Brother, come along with us, Efack you ſhall have Braſs enough to mend.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, Ay, come away, God bleſs the Chriſtian Religion, and hang the Pagans: <hi>Omnes, Amen, Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Come along <hi>Old Bay,</hi> we'll make thee for ever.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>O' my Conſcience they'll make me out of my Wits, if they keep me much longer. <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Come old Boy, throw away that Budget; thou ſhalt have a purſe full of Braſs and Iron.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie</speaker>
                     <p>No, hang it, I'll keep it becauſe 'twas my Fathers: Uds-be as black as the Caſe appears, there's a <hi>heavenly luſtre</hi> within. O my Heart akes for my Jewels.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>7 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Oh! I love this <hi>gutting</hi> of Houſes dearly, my Father was brought up to the Trade.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>8 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I had a Brother liv'd and dy'd in't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>9 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Ay <hi>Tom,</hi> I remember him very well, <hi>I ſaw him cut down.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>10 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Away, away Boys; <hi>holloo, holloo.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>They ſhout, and go off with</hi> Pie.</stage>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:151096:33"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Guard, with</hi> Barbaroſſa <hi>in a Tarpawlins Diſguiſe, follow'd by the Rabble.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
                     <p>For Heavens ſake Sir's, keep me from the <hi>Mob;</hi> and do elſe what you pleaſe with me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Do you hear, the Villain abuſes us, he calls us plain <hi>Mob, without an</hi> M. to it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Ay, ay, a Rogue, he hang'd my Brother in the <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> without ever a Letter in the whole Criſs Croſs Row; He would not let him ſpeak one word or tittle for himſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Hey day! why is this the <hi>Chancellor?</hi> Why he look as if he had been at Sea.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>No, he looks as if he would have been at Sea;</hi> but hang him, he was never born to be drown'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>5 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Why here's a ſtrange alteration; here's the <hi>Judge turn'd Executioner;</hi> he's like the Hangman in the Weſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>6 <hi>Rab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>O the Villain, he hang'd my Father for giving a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of Hay to one of the Lord of <hi>Monumora</hi>'s Horſemen: Oh his tear him to pieces: Guard ſtand off there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt omnes</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Scene IV.</hi> The Palace of St. Jacques.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Prince</hi> Lyfander, <hi>attended with the Nobility and Gentry of</hi> Hungary, <hi>and Guards in a magnificent manner, with Drums beating, Trumpets ſounding,</hi> Colours flying, <hi>the People ſhouting and the Guns round the great Tower firing; at which the Stars clear up, the Sun ſhines, and all the</hi> inchanted Pagan <hi>Moſques Prieſts, Jebuſites, Croſſes, Beads, Quo Warranto's, Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Eccleſiaſtick Commiſſioners,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>vaniſh in a moment.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:151096:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
